<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A consideration of the depriued and silenced ministers arguments, for their restitution to the vse and libertie of their ministerie exhibited in their late supplication, vnto the honorable states assembled in this present Parliament. By Gabriel Powel.</title>
            <author>Powel, Gabriel, 1576-1611.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1606</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 155 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 42 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09880</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20142</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120763</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855957</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855957</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21468</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09880)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21468)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 933:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A consideration of the depriued and silenced ministers arguments, for their restitution to the vse and libertie of their ministerie exhibited in their late supplication, vnto the honorable states assembled in this present Parliament. By Gabriel Powel.</title>
                  <author>Powel, Gabriel, 1576-1611.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 80 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by G. Eld, for Thomas Adams,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1606.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reply to: Certaine arguments to perswade and provoke the most honorable and high court of Parliament now assembled.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank except for signature-mark "A1".</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A consideration of the depriued ministers supplication &amp;c.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Certaine arguments to perswade and provoke the most honorable and high court of Parliament now assembled --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Puritans --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21468:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21468:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Conſideration of the Depriued and Silenced <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters Arguments, for their</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution to the vſe and libertie of <hi>their Miniſterie;</hi> Exhibited in their late Suppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, <hi>vnto the Honorable States</hi> aſſembled in this preſent Parliament.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Gabriel Powel.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Geneſ. 13.8.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>Let there be no ſtrife, I pray thee, betweene thee and me, for we are Bretheren.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>AT LONDON Printed by <hi>G. Eld,</hi> for <hi>Thomas Adams.</hi>
1606.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:21468:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:21468:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honorable, the <hi>Lords Spirituall and Temporall,</hi> the Knights, Cittizens and Burgeſſes <hi>of the high Court of Parliament.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas the <hi>Solon,</hi> or rather the <hi>Salomon</hi> of this age and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchie, our moſt gracious and peereleſſe Soueraigne, hath ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording vnto his ſingular wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and ſinceritie of heart, by all good means, laboured the Reformation, as of all his Subiects in generall, which refuſe to ſerue GOD with vs, in ſuch holy exerciſes of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, as are already eſtabliſhed amongſt vs, ſo eſpecially of ſuch our Brethren in the Miniſterie, as emulating forraine Noveltie, refuſe to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme themſelues vnto the ancient approued diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline and ceremonies of our Church: whom therefore his Highneſſe ſought the more earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie to reclaime, (as he loued them dearlieſt) by ſome correction of their obſtinacie, by Silence and Deprivation, according to the laudable cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome and ſanctions of the Eccleſiaſticall Courts in this behalfe.</p>
            <p>Now (Right Reuerend and Honorable) there are which greatly complaine of this moderate Severitie, and both vnfitly and vndutifully terme it by the moſt hatefull and odious names of <hi>Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſsion</hi> and
<hi>Crueltie;</hi> which they do as well in their private talke, in their publike Sermons and
<pb facs="tcp:21468:3"/>writings, as alſo in a late Supplicatorie Pamphlet directed vnto your graue Wiſdomes, wherin the Auctor is not affraide <hi>to perſwade and prouoke</hi> your Honourable Court (theſe are his owne words) to intercede with his Maieſtie, that he would compell the Reverend Prelates of this Church, to ſurceaſe their rigorous and cruell dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, who haue ſoberly and temperately carried themſelues in the execution of ſuch Decrees and Sentences vpon them, as their obſtinate Superſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion had worthily made them ſubiect vnto. By which boldneſſe he taketh occaſion ſo to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine and crie out, as if the Goſpell of CHRIST IESVS were baniſhed out of this Kingdome, GODS worſhip prophanely adulterated, and our whole Miniſterie ſtrangely corrupted, to the eternall perdition and deſtruction of many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Soules. Which grieuous complainte, ſeeing it cannot be vnknowne to any that liue within theſe Dominions, to be vtterly vniuſt &amp; vntrue, I can but wonder with what face he could once dare to preſent it to the moſt Reuerend Senate of your moſt Honorable and iudicious Court. For howſoeuer hee might perſwade himſelfe, that ſome preiudicate perſons would affect his cauſe, and embrace his accuſations; yet could he never have the leaſt hope, ſo to abuſe your Wiſdomes, who of your owne knowledge are able to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince him of malepert Sycophancie, and manifeſt vntruth. Notwithſtanding all which, this Auctor fearing no rebuke or ſhame for his vnconſciona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble dealing (as ſpeaking from Cimmerian darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb facs="tcp:21468:3"/>by concealing his name) is enboldened to offer it even vnto your Honors, <hi>to prouoke</hi> you to become suppliants and Su<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ters vnto his excellent Maieſty in behalfe of their cauſe, or elſe (at le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth) to Determine of it your ſelues, <hi>before you diſſolue your meeting.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Diſcourſe (ſuch as it is) I was comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded (by ſome in auctoritie) to peruſe, &amp; briefly to refute, which I confeſſe at firſt I was very vnwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to take vpon me; notwithſtanding, I ſaw the great aduantage I ſhould haue of my Brethere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in the defence and maintenance of a moſt iuſt and holy Quarell. For (beſides that I was exceeding loath to intermedle in theſe domeſticall Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſies, and indeed as
<hi>Abram</hi> ſaid vnto <hi>Lot;</hi> (<hi>Gen.</hi> 13.8.) Why ſhould there be ſtrife betweene them and vs, <hi>for we are Brethren?</hi>) I ſaw many excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent witts ſit quietly at their ſtudies, being better furniſhed and more able to deale in theſe caſes then my ſelfe, who come ſo farre behinde them in all ſufficiencie for this purpoſſe. And ſpecially, waighing my owne weakneſſe, I iuſtly feared to practiſe this kinde of pleading in ſo high a Court, and before ſuch Iudges, whoſe wiſedomes can ſo eaſily diſcerne any which come before them. But on the other ſide, when I had throughly weighed the equitie of the Cauſe, the quality of my Voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the neceſſitie of the Church, and the dutie of obeying the Auctoritie, whereby I haue beene enioyned this taske, I preſently reſolued with my ſelfe, to ſtand in the gap and breach betweene our Bretheren and vs, and according to my poore a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:21468:4"/>abilitie, to performe a ſeruice ſo iuſt, holy, dutifull and neceſſarie; albeit I knew my Brethrens af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections to be ſomewhat vnkinde, and their pens foule and ſhameleſſe. But ſeeing it lieth not in our power to make them modeſt and peaceable, and that we are called to ſerue God and his Church, which we are bound to do in good and euill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, in honour and diſhonour, in wealth &amp; wo, in life and death, I willingly forgiue them any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurie that may be done vnto me for this cauſe, and pray our Heauenly Father, that of his infinite mercie and loue in Ieſus Chriſt, he will not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute it vnto them.</p>
            <p>So being ſatiſfied of all ſcruples concerning this matter, and knowing no ſufficient cauſe to the contrary, or other impediment to ſtay my courſe, I haue not withdrawne my ſelfe, no not for the eſtimation and reuerence I muſt needs haue of the grave iudgement of your Honours, which I ſaw I could not eſcape, but haue deemed this Defence to be my moſt bounden dutie to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God, to his excellent Maieſtie, to your honourable Court, and to this whole Church &amp; State. Wherefore I haue preſumed by your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable leaue and fauour, to maintaine againſt this Plaintiffe, to my ſmall power, the glory of God, in the iuſt defence of his Church, and the honour of the reuerend Prelates in their moſt lawfull proceedings, againſt ſuch, as by their ſchiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me and faction, diſturbe the quietneſſe both of our Church and common-weale.</p>
            <p>Thus having in all ſubmiſſion and humilitie,
<pb facs="tcp:21468:4"/>rendred ſome reaſon of this my doing vnto your high and Honorable Court, I come now to ioine iſſue with my Antagoniſt, not doubting but that your Honors, according vnto your rare Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and ſpeciall loue vnto Iuſtice, as you do in all other Cauſes depending among brethren, ſo in this, will giue equall hearing vnto both parties, and (without partiality and preiudicate affection) will iudge <hi>righteous Iudgment,</hi> that is, ſimplie &amp; abſolutely according vnto the trueth.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Title of the Supplication.</head>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Certaine Arguments to <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade and prouoke the moſt honorable and high court</hi> of Parliament now aſſembled, and alſo all other in any high authority, or in any grace, and credit with them that are in high authority, to promote and aduance the ſincere Miniſtery of the Goſpell; as alſo Zealouſly to ſpeake for the Miniſters thereof now Degraded, Deprived, Silenced, or Admoniſhed, or after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward like to be called into queſtion, for Subſcription, Ceremonies, ſtrict obſervation of the booke of common prayer, or for other conformity.</p>
               <q>
                  <p>Them that honor me I will honor: and they that deſpiſe me, ſhall be deſpiſed.</p>
                  <bibl>1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.30.</bibl>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <p>He that is not with me, is againſt me: and he that gathereth not with me, ſcattereth.</p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 12.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>0.</bibl>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Therefore,</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <p>Watch yee: ſtand faſt in the faith; quit you like men, and be ſtrong.</p>
                  <bibl>1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.13.</bibl>
               </q>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:21468:5"/>
            <head>To the Chriſtian<note n="a)" place="margin">What here is pretended to the Reader in generall, is indeed ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally intended and directed vnto the Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament: as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter end of this firſt <hi>Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graph.</hi>
               </note> Reader, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable, Worſhipfull. &amp;c.</head>
            <p>TOuching theſe arguments following, my humble petition to the<note n="b)" place="margin">This pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence vnto the <hi>Chriſtian Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> is becauſe they wold not ſeeme to be petitioners vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> Chriſtian reader (of whatſoeuer ſort and condition) is this, that they may not be taken as proceeding from one ſuſpecting any religious Noble man or Gentleman of the Parliament houſe, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from one as with all thanks to God, acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the godly forwardneſſe of many in both houſes, ſo alſo earneſtly deſiring to quicken the zeale of the beſt, and to provoke all other, to take the cauſe heere hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to heart, not onely as the cauſe of poore diſtreſſed men, but as the cauſe of God; yea to accompt it alſo the<note n="c)" place="margin">The Suppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ants make the profeſſion of the Goſpell &amp; all Religion, to conſiſt in refuſing <hi>cap, ſurplice, croſſe,</hi> &amp;c Great crie little wooll.</note> maine cauſe of the whole land, of your ſelues and all your poſteritie, and therefore to preferre the ſame <hi>(according to the dayly moſt godly prayer of your ſelues, in your houſe of Parliament)</hi> before al other cauſes whatſoeuer, either concerning any par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular perſons, or the whole common wealth.</p>
            <p>Whereas I haue perſwaded them to whom I haue directed theſe reaſons, to vſe all meanes they may for the doing of any good; I deſire that my wordes may not be vncharitablie conſtrued, of any other
<hi>meanes</hi> then ſuch, as are ſutable to the <hi>cauſe,</hi> viz. of good ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, lawfull, peaceable and agreeable to euery mans calling. The like charitable conſtruction I craue of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other wordes, which ſome perhaps may maliciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wreſt againſt my ſelfe and the cauſe.</p>
            <p>Whereas alſo ſome may ſeeme to pretend feare of his moſt excellent Maieſties<note n="d)" place="margin">As if his Maieſty wold be
<hi>diſpleaſed,</hi> if any promoted a religious or honeſt cauſe. A malepert &amp; preſumptuous <hi>(if not diſloyal)</hi> Cenſure.</note> diſpleaſure to hinder
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:21468:5"/>their zeale and courage, ſuch I intreat to conſider, how diſhonourable (if not diſloyall) it is in good cauſes to feare the diſpleaſure of a Prince, who beſides his moſt Chriſtian education from his infancy, hath<note n="e)" place="margin">I know not whereto all his whole pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragraph tend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth if the Suppliants deeme not his Maieſty to haue forſaken his firſt loue and to haue reuolted from Religion, at leaſt in ſhevv for a time.</note> long time publikly giuen ſo many worthy teſtimonies of his piety and godlineſſe. <hi>Loue thinketh no evill of any,</hi> much leſſe of ſuch a Chriſtian Prince. <hi>It beleeueth all, and hopeth all of euery brother,</hi> much more of a religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous King. <hi>It is the glory of a King</hi> not only <hi>to finde out the ſecrets of other,</hi> but alſo ſometime to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceale his own. Therfore it is not meete by preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t words or deedes, (whereof ſometime there may bee a deepe reaſon) alwaies to iudge of the mind. <hi>Iehu</hi> pretended one thing (when he proclaimed a ſacrifice for <hi>Baal</hi>) but hee intended another:
<hi>Ioſeph</hi> a long time dealt roughly (both in word and deede) with his brethren yet in the end he ſhewed himſelfe moſt louing and kinde vnto them. Our <hi>Sauiour</hi> (for the triall of the woman of <hi>Canaan</hi>) ſeemed a long time to repel her ſute, for her daughter, firſt by ſilence, <hi>2.</hi> by a ſharpe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion of his diſciples, petitioning in her behalfe: and <hi>3.</hi> by a more ſharp anſwer to her ſelfe. At the laſt notwithſtanding, he did moſt graciouſly open the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of his rich compaſsion towards her, and ſent her away with aboundant comfort. <hi>Conſtantius</hi> the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the <hi>Great</hi> (as <hi>Euſebius</hi> repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, lib. <hi>1. de vita Conſtantini,</hi> cap. <hi>11.</hi>) at his firſt entrance into the Empire, made ſolemne proclamati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that all <hi>which</hi>
               <note n="f)" place="margin">A malicious vncharitable, &amp; vnchriſtian allegation, to be applied vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the whole ſtate (that loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally obey his Maieſty) eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially his No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants. <hi>See the Anſwer.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>ſerued him in his court, ſhould either worſhip Devills,</hi> (after the manner of the Heathen) <hi>or giue ouer their places of dignity and honour, and ſo to be baniſhed from his court.</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:21468:6"/>
               <hi>But by this meanes when he had tryed them that were faithfull, then (to the farre greater honour of his Princely wiſedome and piety, than if he had plainely and ſimply at the firſt profeſſed the Chriſtian religion) He diſgraced thoſe that had ſo reuolted from God, and rebuked them with a moſt Princely and religious rebuke, ſaying,</hi> That they were Traytors to GOD, and vnworthy the ſeruice of an Emperour. For how <hi>(quoth he)</hi> can they keepe faith vnuiolate to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Emperour, which are manifeſtly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinced to be vnfaithfull to the moſt excellent and mighty God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>On the contrarie, thoſe that for conſcience had forſake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their places, and giuen ouer their honors, he moſt high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly graced,</hi> as thoſe that would be faithfull to the Emperour, becauſe they had beene ſo vnto God: yea, he pronounced them worthy to be reckoned among the chiefe and principall friends of the Emperour, and to be worthily much more eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med then Treaſuryes full of great riches. <hi>There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore alſo he preferred ſome of them to ſpeciall atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance vpon his owne perſon, and other ſome hee aduanced to the chiefe gouernement of the Empire vnder himſelfe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I leaue the</hi>
               <note n="g)" place="margin">For if they had particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly applyed theſe things, their malice had bin the more manifeſt</note> 
               <hi>application of theſe things. Onely I wiſh ſuch conſideration of them, that men may not bee raſh (vpon any ſuppoſed apparences) to iudge Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Princes, eſpecially who in former times haue many wayes teſtified their ſincere religion: yea I wiſh leſſe cenſuring</hi>
               <note n="h)" place="margin">No bolder and ſecurer cenſurers of al ſorts and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of men vnder the cope of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, then theſe ſingular and ſelfe conceip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Refracta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries.</note> 
               <hi>of them, and more earneſt praying for them</hi> in ſecret, before him that ſeeeth in ſecret and hath promiſed to reward openly: yea as <hi>Dauid</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:21468:6"/>bleſſed the Lord God of Iſraell, and the counſell of <hi>Abigail,</hi> and <hi>Abigail</hi> her ſelfe, for keeping him from ſheading innocent blood, 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 25.32. <hi>&amp;c. ſo (to omit what</hi>
               <note n="i)" place="margin">How prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall they are of the Kings thankes!</note> 
               <hi>thankes you may haue from his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Maieſty) who alſo knoweth, how euen they, that for the preſent do moſt reſiſt the matters hereafter pleaded for, will in the end bleſſe God and your coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, and your ſelues, for ſtaying them from their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding in their hard courſes againſt</hi>
               <note n="k)" place="margin">An euident ſlander of the State: as if no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me were the
<hi>Miniſtery of the Goſpell.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>the miniſtery of the Goſpell, and the ſaluation of the people depending thereupon?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Finally, albeit I could haue added many other ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments to theſe that I haue here written for the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther whetting of the zeale of thoſe to whom theſe cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes principally appertaine yet ſeeing theſe doe ariſe to ſuch a</hi>
               <note n="l)" place="margin">Is a triobo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Pamphlet ſuch a huge <hi>quantity</hi> or volume? It might ſeeme the pen-man of this Suppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation was the worthy Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of many of the late two leand Libels.</note> 
               <hi>quantity: I thought it beſt to ſpare the further paynes of my ſelfe, and of the reader: hoping that theſe which I haue written ſhall be ſufficient ſo to kindle the zeale of them that loue the Lord Ieſus and his trueth,</hi> that they ſhalbe ſo full of matter (<hi>as</hi>
               <note n="m)" place="margin">Such pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous &amp; ſelfe conceip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Elibues</hi> are theſe mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, who take vpon them to inſtruct ſuch as be wiſer then them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues. <hi>Vide Gregorin hunc locum.</hi>
               </note> Elihu <hi>ſpeaketh of himſelfe</hi>) Iob.
32.19. that their ſpirit within them, ſhall compell them, and that their bellies ſhall be as the wine which hath no vent, and like the new bottels that burſt, that ſo they may ſpeake to take breath, and open their lips, for anſwer of them <hi>(if any ſuch do ſhew themelues) that do oppugne, or ſhall oppugne the ſincere miniſtery of the Goſpell. In which hope</hi> I commend them to God, and to the word of his Grace.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:21468:7"/>
            <head>A Conſideration of the Preface.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the Preface, by way of Antici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation, the Authors of this Suppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation labour to expreſſe their meaning more plainely, and to cleare ſome wordes and phraſes, which otherwiſe might ſeeme ſubiect to miſſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation, and (as they ſpeake) to <hi>vncharita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble conſtruction:</hi> which cautelous dealing verily is moſt neceſſarie in this carping age, wherein the common Aduerſarie, to couer his own ſhame for his rebellious and traiterous Poſitions and Practiſes, lieth houering in the winde, ready to catch at any thing that may aduantage himſelfe, and preiudice our cauſe.</p>
            <p>And ſurely for my own part, I am ſo farre from taking any exception againſt my Brethren in this kinde,<note place="margin">Of the obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of Preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians towards their Prince.</note> that I verily thinke, that all wee pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing the Goſpell within this kingdome of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, howſoeuer ſome haue foliſhly made a breach &amp; diuiſion amongſt vs, about Croſſe, Surplice, &amp;c. doe as hartily and faithfully loue, &amp; as dutifully affect and imbrace our Prince or King (yea of whatſoeuer Religion) and are as ready and willing to defend his Perſon and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour againſt all aduerſarie power or treacherous attempt whatſoeuer, as any other people or na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion vnder the ſunne.</p>
            <p>Wherefore, as I cannot allow the opinion of ſuch as giue out, that theſe our factious Brethren, <hi>are as dangerous enemies vnto the State, as the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pistes,</hi> thoſe Antichriſtian and bloody Traytours,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:21468:7"/>that neuer are faithfull vnto any, but vnto the Pope and the Diuell: So I cannot but worthily commend that memorable apothegme of that reuerend and learned Prelate <hi>Doctor Elmer</hi> of happy memory, ſometimes L. Byſhop of Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, who when this queſtion was debated in his hearing, grauely anſwered. <hi>If I were in the compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny but of one Papiſt, I might iuſtly feare the loſſe of my life, but being amongſt ten thouſand Preciſians well might I be affrayde of my Byſhoprike, but neuer of my throate.</hi> And againe,<note place="margin">An Apotheg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me of Biſhop Elmer,</note> 
               <hi>The one would cut my coate, and the other my throate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Neither doe I ſpeake this, abſolutely to free ſuch as be Refractarie among vs, from all diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience vnto Magiſtrates, but onely from ſuſpici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Treaſon and Rebellion. For otherwiſe it cannot be denied,<note place="margin">That Preciſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans are Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticall and turbulent.</note> but that preſumptuouſly and wilfully they contend with the Magiſtrate, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugning his authoritie in things indifferent, and ſoueraigntie in Eccleſiaſtical cauſes (though not in the ſame ſenſe and degree as the Papiſtes do) and alſo that they make a faction and manifeſt Schiſme in the Church of GOD: which all of them do for carnall reſpectes:<note place="margin">And why</note> ſome becauſe they knowe not otherwiſe howe to be maintayned but by depending vpon that faction, ſome to gratifie their Benefactors and Patrons, and to pleaſe their Friends, ſome for diſcontentment and want of preferment, ſome for giddineſſe of innouation, ſome for pride of heart and ſelf-loue, ſome for hatred of order and reſtraint of their libertie, ſome ſtill to retaine the opinion of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:21468:8"/>in perſeuering ſingular, and others of mere ignorance. which yet is wilful and affected, ſeeing they will not learne the State of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſie which they are bound to know, and therefore cannot be excuſed.</p>
            <p>But two things ſpecially may be iuſtly cenſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and taxed in this Preface: whereof the firſt is, that herein they haue quite altered the ſtate of the queſtion in controuerſie, betweene vs: which ſurely argueth a deſperate diffidence to preuaile in their ſuite, by declining the
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall matter of difference: For, whereas it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed by themſelues, aſwell in the very Title, as afterwards in the Booke it ſelfe <hi>Arg.</hi> 16. <hi>&amp; Arg.</hi> 18. that the whole controuerſie betweene vs is, but about <hi>Subſcription, Ceremonies, the ſtrict obſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the booke of Commen Prayer, and other Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formitie</hi> vnto the Diſcipline and order of our Church (for this I take to bee their meaning) which are but matters of indifferency and of ſmal moment in themſelues: Now they ſeeme to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt it, forſooth, <hi>the Cauſe of GOD, the Miniſterie of the Goſpell, the ſaluation of the people, the maine cauſe of the land, of all the States</hi> of this kingdome
<hi>and all their poſteritie;</hi> and ſuch a cauſe, as is <hi>to be preferred before al other cauſes whatſoeuer, either co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning any particular perſons, or the whole Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth:</hi> as if all Religion and Pietie depended vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on refuſing of Croſſe &amp; Surplice, and ſuch other accidentall circumſtances.</p>
            <p>The Latter is, that they boldly, preſumptuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and vndutifully cenſure his Maieſtie, for coldeneſſe in Religion, in relinquiſhing his former
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:21468:8"/>profeſſion, or at leaſt for deepe diſſembling in ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to pretend one thing, &amp; to intend another: as if he had bin trained vp &amp; taught in the Ieſuits ſchooles, to Equivocate: (which fault, would God, ſome of their factio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; followers did ſo little practiſe, as his Highnes abhors it.) Whereas his Highneſſe religious heart is euidently and eaſily diſcerned, to be fully ſeaſoned with true pietie and devotion, aſwell by his preſent ſincere pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of the Goſpell, and vnfained loue vnto the Miniſters thereof, as alſo by daily effects of ſaith and a good conſcience, which as ſweete ſmelling fruites do liuely demonſtrate the goodneſſe and excellencie of the tree. But I referre the farther conſideration of this point vnto your graue wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes: onely it ſuffiſeth me to haue detected the licenſe of their raving pens, the reſtraint of which furie, ſpecially belongeth vnto your Honourable &amp; iudicious Court. Which (queſtionles) your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours will the rather performe, conſidering what an vnchriſtian conceipt they haue aſwell of your Honourable Aſſemblie, as alſo of all other his Maieſties louing Subiects and Seruants, who loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally obey him &amp; ſerue the Lord of Hoſtes, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vnto the Religion eſtabliſhed; as is manifeſt by their inſtance and allegation of that example of the Emperour
<hi>Conſtantius</hi> his Nobles, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came Idolaters and Atheiſts, to curry fauour with the Emperour: as alſo becauſe afterwards, <hi>in the</hi>
8. <hi>Argument,</hi> they boldly cenſure your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, as <hi>not regarding the Church, nor the cauſe of God,</hi> faining moreouer, how <hi>GOD and his ſonne
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:21468:9"/>CHRIST IESVS ſtand, as it were, at your Parliament Houſe dore knocking, and crauing to be let in,</hi> inſinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ating thereby, that GOD is not Preſident of your honorable Aſſemblie, and that all your godly and Religious Acts haue beene hetherto decreed and concluded, I know not by what ſpirit. Now let vs examine their Arguments.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="answer">
            <head>Certaine Arguments to prouoke this preſent high Court of Parliament to zeale, for the Miniſters now ſilenced.</head>
            <head type="sub">ANSWER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He maine Propoſition of this Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication is this, <hi>All the Nobles and States aſſembled in the preſent Court of Parliament, are bound, zealouſly to ſpeake for the Miniſters now degraded, depriued, ſilenced, or admoniſhed, or afterward like to be called into queſtion, for Subſcription, Ceremonies, ſtrict obſeruation of the Booke of Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon Praier, or for other Conformity.</hi> This Propoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> being laid down almoſt in ſo many words, both in the generall ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of the Booke, and alſo in the 16. &amp; 18. <hi>Arg.</hi> the Suppliants labour to proue by XIIX. ſundrie Reaſons, all which, albeit they be Common Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments (excepting one or two) and may be vr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged for Poperie, or any other Hereſie what ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, which the learned know to be an intolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble fault in a Scholler, &amp; were a ſufficient anſwer vnto them all; yet we will examine the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſeuerally.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="1" type="argument">
            <head>I. ARGVMENT.</head>
            <p>FOr the ground of all that followeth (to<note n="a)" place="margin">That is but iuſtly omitted that can make nothing to the purpoſe.</note> omit with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out long diſcourſe that principall point that the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:21468:9"/>Goſpell is the power of God vnto ſalvation (as that which I hope is doubted of none:) It is to be conſidered that the Miniſters in particular aboue mentioned, are the<note n="b)" place="margin">So be others alſo, which (I hope) the Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliants will not deny.</note> Miniſters of Chriſt, ſent by God, and ingrace &amp; favor with God. This is<note n="c)" place="margin">They might haue ſpared la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing what we never denied. And yet their proofes are ſuch, that they proue not their intent.</note> euident. <hi>1.</hi>
               <note n="d)" place="margin">Palpable ignorance. Many lay-men are 1. <hi>hated of the world.</hi> 2. <hi>lead an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blamable life.</hi> and 3. <hi>haue ſufficient gifts.</hi> Ergo, They are Miniſters of Chriſt, ſent by God, &amp;c. Inconſequent. Abſurd.</note> By the hatred of all ſorts of the wicked and vngodly men, Papists, Atheiſts, &amp; Carnall Goſpellers, in ſpeciall manner a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them. <hi>If yee were of the world</hi> (ſaith our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour,)
<hi>the world would loue his owne, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe yee are not of the world, but I haue choſen you out of the world, therefore the world hateth you. Ioh.
15.19. 2.</hi> By their vnblameable life<note n="e)" place="margin">They haue ill neighbours that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mend themſelues. But I could wiſh they wer ſuch indeed: albeit they are generally no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to be great teachers and practiſers of vſury.</note> in all other things, the matter onely of Conformity excepted. This hath bin and daily is acknowledged by<note n="f)" place="margin">Why do not you name them?</note> thoſe that are Iudges againſt them for the ſaid Conformity. And albeit contempt, ſingularity and ambition be obiected vnto them, yet how vniuſtly this is obiected, doth<note n="g)" place="margin">All this euidence can make but a coniecture, &amp; that ſcarce probable, ſeeing many Heretiques, Papiſts, &amp;c. haue ſuffred nore then all this comes to, for their hereſie &amp; ſuperſtition.</note> evidently appeare by the manifold reproches, the great moleſtations, loſſe of liuing, to the vndoing of themſelues, their wiues &amp; Children, and many other wrongs, iniuries, and indignities which they haue ſuffred and dayly doe ſuffer. <hi>3.</hi> As by their<note n="h)" place="margin">As we enuie not their <hi>gifts,</hi> ſo we co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mend their <hi>paines,</hi> &amp; wiſh that they had not put then hands to the plough and looked back, &amp;c.</note> gifts wherewith they are furniſhed for their callings, and by their paines and diligence accordingly in their callings, ſo eſpecially by the bleſsing of GOD vpon<note n="i)" place="margin">It ſeemes they fauour the doctrine <hi>De opere operantis:</hi> eſpecially waighing the latter part of this phariſaicall compariſon.</note> their ſaid paines and diligence in the knowledge and obedience of the people, in ſuch places where they liue, and in the mutuall loue and peace of ſuch
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:21468:10"/>people among them ſelues: whereas in other places men, for the moſt parte, are<note n="a)" place="margin">They com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues by diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gracing o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. A lying and malicious cenſure.</note> ignorant of all duty to God and man, and therefore prophane, irreligious, contentious, and apt to ſedition and rebellion, as all experience teacheth vs. This argument iuſtifieth their<note n="b)" place="margin">It is not their calling, but innouati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and ſchi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me that is bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med.</note> calling. For howe could they ſo preach to ſuch effectes of knowledge,<note n="c)" place="margin">The Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fractarie fac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion haue no great cauſe to brag of theſe effects in themſelues.</note> Godlineſſe, loyalty peace and loue, except they were ſent, <hi>Rom. 10.15.</hi> That which the Apoſtle ſaith to the Corinthians in the like be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe touching his Apoſtleſhip, may alſo be ſaid in this touching the miniſtery and calling of theſe men vnto thoſe people where they are, and among whome the Lord hath ſo bleſſed their miniſteriall laboure, <hi>Are ye not my worke in the Lord? If I be not an Apoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle to other, yet doubtles I am vnto you for ye are the ſeale of my Apoſtleſhip in the Lord. 1. Cor. 9.1.2.</hi> And Againe, <hi>ye are our Epiſtle written in our heartes, which is vnderſtood &amp; read of all men, in that ye are manifeſted to be the Epiſtle of Chriſt, miniſtred by vs, &amp; witten not with inke, but with the ſpirit of the lyuing God, not in tables of ſtone, but in fleſhly tables of the heart. 2. Cor.
3.2.3.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sith it is ſo; not to ſpeake &amp; put forth your ſelues in behalf of theſe men, is to ſpare ſpeach and paines for<note n="d)" place="margin">As if the Refractarie Miniſters Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition and ſchiſme were Gods cauſe.</note> God himſelfe &amp; for Chriſt Ieſus. <hi>Ex.
16.2. 1. Sam. 8.7. Lu. 10.16.</hi> If they are ſaid to deny bodily food, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parrel &amp; lodging vnto Chriſt himſelf, that deny theſe things to the leaſt of his elect, <hi>Math. 25.40.</hi> May not they much more be ſaid, to ſpare ſpeech and paines for Chriſt, that ſpare their ſpeech &amp; paines for the euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting<note n="e)" place="margin">As if the kingdome of heauen conſiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in meate, drinke or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther outward thing. Groſſe impudency, or blinde ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance.</note> ſaluation of many thouſand ſolues? Yea this cannot be denied, ſith all the<note n="f)" place="margin">They ſpare ſpeech for Chriſt VVhea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore? Becauſe the Godly haue put on the Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus &amp;c. A ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</note> Godly
<hi>haue put on the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:21468:10"/>Lord Ieſus, Gal. 3.25. And are fleſh of his fleſh &amp; bone of his bones. Epheſ. 5.30.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Finally, let this argument the more preuaile with all men, in regard of al that Chriſt Ieſus (whoſe cauſe this is (<note n="a)" place="margin">Where, when, and by-whom?</note> ſhewed to be) hath ſuffered and done for vs.</p>
            <div type="resolution">
               <head>Reſolution of the 1. Argument.</head>
               <p>The Refractary Miniſters are the Miniſters of Chriſt ſent by God, and in grace &amp; fauor with God. Not to ſpeake for them, is to ſpare ſpeech, for God himſelfe, for Chriſt Ieſus (Ex.
<hi>16.2.1.</hi> Sa. <hi>8.7.</hi> Lu. <hi>10.16.</hi>) &amp; for the euerlaſting ſaluation of many thouſand ſoules. <hi>Ergo.</hi> The Honorable and high Court of Parliament ought to intercede with his Maieſtie for them.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="answer">
            <head>ANSWER.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>I.</hi> To the Antecedent.</head>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> WE willingly grant that the Refractary Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters are indeed <hi>the Miniſters of Chriſt</hi> in the miniſtration of his Goſpel, neither is their calling brought in queſtion: &amp; we hope alſo that they are <hi>ſent by GOD, &amp; in grace and fauor with GOD.</hi> Yet muſt they remember, that their Sanctification be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in part, they haue but their meaſure of giftes &amp; graces: for <hi>our knowledge is but in part,</hi> as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle teſtifieth; &amp; therefore that they may be ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant &amp; ouerſeene in ſome things, wherein they ought not to flatter themſelues, but by al meanes labour to come to vnderſtanding, that they may attaine vnto the knowledge of the trueth.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It is true alſo, that <hi>not to ſpeake and take paines for the Miniſters of the Goſpell,</hi> for ſuch
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:21468:11"/>things as properly belong vnto their Miniſterie, or are requiſite vnto the performance thereof, is <hi>to ſpare ſpeech for GOD, and for Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vnto the places quoted in the Argument, and alſo <hi>to hinder the ſaluation of Gods people.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. The Errour is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. This is not the Refractary Miniſters caſe: wherefore I anſwere</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>II. To the Conſequence.</head>
               <p n="1">1. If the Suppliants had prayed your High Court of Parliament to intreate in their behalfe for matters which had neceſſarily concerned <hi>the Goſpel of Chriſt,</hi> or their <hi>Miniſterie thereof,</hi> or <hi>the Saluation of many thouſand Soules,</hi> then had your Honorable Aſſemblie ſome reaſon to mediate for them: But ſeeing it is but onely to free them from the <hi>Croſſe</hi> and
<hi>Surplice,</hi> and ſuch other lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable <hi>ceremonies</hi> of our Church, commanded for order and decencie ſake, which may well ſtand with the purity of the Goſpell, ſeeing <hi>the kingdome of heauen ſtandes not in meate and drinke. &amp;c.</hi> Then haue theſe importunate Suppliants greater reaſon patiently to beare that burden in the diligent applying their vocation and calling, then to trouble your Wiſdomes with ſuch petty and ſmall matters.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Errour is two fold. 1. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 2.
<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="argument">
            <head>II. <hi>ARGVMENT.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>IT is alſo to be conſidered that the miniſtery of the Goſpell, is not onely for earthly men, but alſo<note n="a)" place="margin">An abſurde Paradore.</note> for heauenly Angels. Therefore as the Cherubins were

<pb n="19" facs="tcp:21468:11"/>commaunded to be ſet <hi>with their faces towards the Mercy ſeate. Exod. 25.20.</hi> as looking and liſtening after the Oracles of God that ſhould be giuen from the mercy ſeate to the Church ſo it is not onely ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what obſcurely ſaid concerning <hi>thoſe things that are ſhewed by them that preach the Goſpell by the holy Ghoſt, that the Angels doe</hi>
               <note n="b)" place="margin">
                  <hi>What con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence is this?</hi> The An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels deſire to ſee into the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>crets of our Red inption. <hi>Ergo.</hi> The Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterie of the Goſpell is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for them. A bacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo ad angulum.</note> 
               <hi>deſire to behold the ſaide things, 1. Pet. 1.12.</hi> But leaſt any man ſhould thinke that to be vnderſtood onely of the accompliſhing of the matters preached in the finall, and perfect ſalvation of the elect and whole Church, it is alſo plainely and moſt perſpicuouſly written, that one chiefe ende, purpoſe, and intent of
<hi>preaching the ſaid Goſpell, and the vnſearchable riches of Chriſt in the Goſpell contained,</hi> and of making cleere <hi>vnto all men the fellowſhip of the miſtery of the Goſpell,</hi> was this, <hi>that now vnto principa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities and powers in heavenly places,</hi> (that is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Angels)
<hi>might be knowne by the Church</hi> (not the great ſalvation of the Lord)
<hi>but the manifolde wiſdome of God. Epheſ. 3.10.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To ſpeake therefore for the Goſpell, and for the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere miniſtery &amp; Miniſters therof is to ſpeake not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for<note n="c)" place="margin">But to ſpeake in a ſchiſmaticall cauſe, is to ſpeake neither for <hi>God</hi> nor for <hi>Angels.</hi>
               </note> God, but alſo for the Angels. To ſpare ſpeaking and other paines taking for the<note n="d)" place="margin">Their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention with vs is neither about the <hi>Goſpell,</hi> nor <hi>the ſincere Miniſterie thereof.</hi>
               </note> Goſpell and ſincere miniſtery therof, is to ſpare ſpeaking and taking paines for God him ſelfe &amp; for his bleſſed Angels: and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently, to provoke both the Lord himſelfe of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and earth, and alſo the whole hoſt and army of heaven againſt vs. For, what elſe may bee hoped for where there will not ſo much as earneſt words bee ſpoken for God, or for his Angels?</p>
            <div type="resolution">
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:21468:12"/>
               <head>Reſolution of the 2. Argument.</head>
               <p>The Miniſterie of the Goſpell is not onely for earthly men, but alſo for heauenly Angels. To ſpeake for the Miniſtrie and Miniſters thereof, is to ſpeake not onely for GOD, but alſo for the Angels.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ergo.</hi> The high Court of Parliament is bound, to plead for the Miniſters: otherwiſe by ſparing ſpeach, they ſhall prouoke both the Lord himſelfe, and alſo the whole hoſte and armie of heauen againſt them.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="answer">
            <head>ANSWER.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>1.</hi> To the Antecedent.</head>
               <p n="1">1. THat the <hi>Miniſterie of the Goſpell is for An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels,</hi> is an ambiguous &amp; perplexed ſpeech. and ſauours of a Paradoxe. For how will the Suppliants vnderſtand this ſaying? Is the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie of the Goſpell, ſo ordained for Angels, that they ſhould be Miniſters thereof? Vnpoſſible. Is the Miniſterie ordained to conuert them, and to preach repentance vnto them? Abſurd. Seeing they never ſinned. Or is it becauſe thereby they might learne and know the Wiſedome of God? But ſo do they alſo by all other the creatures and actions of God.</p>
               <p n="2">2. What can this make for the Suppliants? The Controuerſie betweene them and vs, is not concerning the <hi>Miniſterie of the Goſpell,</hi> but tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching a few pettie accidentall circumſtances: for which, if any man forſake the neceſſarie function of his Miniſterie and calling, he hath the more to anſwer for.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Every man is bound to promote the <hi>Miniſtery
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:21468:12"/>of the Goſpell</hi> to his power, and alſo to helpe and further a Miniſter thereof, as he is a Miniſter, not as he is in error, or carried away with faction.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The Errour is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>in Theologia.</hi> Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>II.</hi> To the Conſequence.</head>
               <p n="1">1. It doth not follow, that becauſe the wiſe and iudicious aſſemblie of Parliament iuſtly refuſe to intermeddle in the quarell of Schiſmaticall Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, farther then to admoniſh them to deſiſt from their ſingularity and turbulent dealing, that therefore they ſhall prouoke the Lord of Hoſtes and all the Angels and Saints in heauen againſt them. But rather it followeth on the contrary.</p>
               <p n="2">2. If that Honourable Court ſhould take part with Schiſmatikes, and intercede for them, to detaine both them and the people ſtill in faction and error, then certainly they ſhould prouoke the wrath of God, and the whole hoſt of heauen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them: <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.17.18. &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The Errour is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="argument">
            <head>III. ARGVMENT.</head>
            <p>AS<note n="a)" place="margin">This &amp; the moſt part of the ſubſeque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Arguments are grounded vpon a falſe principle, to wit, that the Refractary Miniſters quarell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Church of England, is the
<hi>Miniſtery of the Goſpel,</hi> the <hi>Saluation of the people.</hi> &amp;c. Whereas indeed all the contention is about Croſſe, Surplice, and ſome other in different Ceremonies &amp; Actions in the Church. And all theſe Argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts do make ſpecially againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſeeing they be onely diſturbers of the ſincere profeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Goſpell &amp; worke of the Miniſtery, yea ſeeing they forſake their calling &amp; moue ſo great concentions and brawles about ſo ſmall matters.</note>
               <hi>Ioſeph</hi> hauing interpreted the dreame of <hi>Pharaoh</hi> his chiefe Butler, touching his reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation againe to the grace of <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> and the reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery of his former place of honourable ſeruice before Pharaoh,
<hi>deſired him to hace him in eeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance, when he ſhould be reconciled and reſtored, Gen.
<pb facs="tcp:21468:13"/>40.41.</hi> So it is recorded by the holy Ghoſt, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged by the ſaid Butler <hi>as a great fault, that he had not remembred</hi> Ioſeph <hi>but forgotten him. Gen. 40.23. &amp; 41.9.</hi> If it were ſo great a fault in <hi>Pharao</hi> his butler not to remember and ſpeake for one <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> that had interpreted one dreame touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his reconcilement to a mortall Prince, and the recouery of an earthly preferment, (neyther of which notwithſtanding he knew not how long he ſhuld enioy, at the moſt he could not enioy them any longer then during onely naturall life) how great them is the fault of all thoſe, that neglect to ſpeake for many miniſters of the Goſpell, that haue not once, but often, and day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly interpreted many myſteries of God, touching their reconciliation with God himſelfe and their euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting aduancement <hi>in heauenly places. Epheſ. 2.6. To walke in white with Chriſt Ieſus, yea to ſit alſo with him in his throne, as he himſelfe ſitteth in the throne of his Father? Apoc. 3.5. &amp; 21.</hi> Yea verily, as the fault of the
<hi>Butler</hi> was the leſse, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe being enlarged, he had none to remember him of that duty ſo the fault of thoſe ſhalbe the greater, that haue many<note n="b)" place="margin">Would God they were half ſo diligent in a good cauſe as they are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunate to ſow ſchiſme &amp; ſedition a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theren. But they deſerue ſmall co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation and thankes of any good Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an for their importunity and earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe herein.</note> dayly to put them in mind thereof, and to prouoke them therevnto, and yet for all that doe hold their peace.</p>
            <div type="resolution">
               <head>Reſolution of the 3. Argument.</head>
               <p>It is a ſinne not to recompence a good turne receiued.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ergo.</hi> The refractary Ministers are to be regarded &amp; ſpoken for.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="answer">
            <head>ANSWER.</head>
            <p n="1">1. It is true good deedes muſt be rewarded, ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:21468:13"/>the Miniſters faithfull labours. The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſaith (1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.11. <hi>If we haue ſowen vnto you ſpirituall things is it a great thing &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. But in that the Refractary Miniſters haue <hi>looked backe,</hi> and withdrawne their hands from the plough. <hi>Luk.</hi> 9.62. making a manifeſt ſchiſme and diſturbing the peace of the Church, this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerueth no recompence.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The errour is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. And
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="argument">
            <head>IV. ARGVMENT.</head>
            <p>THe whole Armie of Iſraell ſpake with great cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage in behalfe of <hi>Ionathan</hi> thus, <hi>Shall</hi> Iona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than <hi>dye who hath mightely deliuered Iſrael? God forbid. As the Lord liueth, there ſhall not one hayre of his head fall to the ground, for hee hath wrought with God this day. 1. Sam. 14.45.</hi> Were this common people that liued vnder the Lawe, and which had not had ſo plentifull and cleare inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction as is now reuealed by the Goſpel: were this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon people (I ſay) ſo<note n="a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ionathans</hi> caſe and the Schiſmatical Miniſters is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, <hi>See the Anſwer.</hi> And the vrging of this
<hi>zeale,</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing not the like cauſe, ſeemes to be very da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gerous But I ſpare my Brethren.</note> zealous for Ionathan in regard onely of a bodily deliuerance, from bodily enimies, whereof he had not beene the Author, but onely an inſtrument of God; and ſhall not this high Court of Parliament now aſſembled, being the chiefe flower of this whole Realme of England and repreſenting the whole Realme, bee zealous and earnest for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny whom God hath vſed as his inſtruments, and who haue wrought with God, and daily would ſo worke with God (if<note n="b)" place="margin">The grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is their ſin, whoſe Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition &amp; wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful obſtinacy hath reſtray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned their li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, &amp; made them vnſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiceable in the Church.</note> they may haue liberty) for the ſpiritual deliuerance of many thouſands fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſpirituall enimies,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:21468:14"/>
               <hi>euen</hi> to turne them from darkeneſſe to light, &amp; from the power of Satan to God, that they may haue for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuenes of ſinnes, &amp; inheritance among them that are ſanctified by faith in Chriſt. Act. <hi>26.18.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="resolution">
               <head>Reſolution of the 4. Argument.</head>
               <p>Such whom the Lord hath made his instruments, for the ſpirituall deliuerance of many thouſands from ſpirituall enemies, are to be reſpected and recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ergo.</hi> The Refractary Miniſters are to be remembred and reſtored.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="answer">
            <head>ANSWER.</head>
            <p n="1">1. This Argument is paralell vnto the former, and is there fully anſwered.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Miniſters, in <hi>deliuering thouſands from ſpirituall enemies,</hi> did but their duty, for which they deſerue loue of the people and commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of all men: but they ſhould ſtill haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued faithfull in their Miniſtery, and not ſham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully haue forſaken their calling.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Ionathans</hi> example, alleadged by the Suppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ants, is vnlike vnto the Miniſters caſe. For <hi>Saul</hi> in deepe hypocriſie, had made a raſhe vowe, that whoſoeuer did <hi>taſte any foode &amp;c.</hi> (1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 14.24.) ſhould be <hi>accurſed, and die the death,</hi> wherefore the people iuſtly reſcued him from the fury of
<hi>Saul.</hi> But the actions of our dread Soueraigne are not ſo exorbitant, they are not raſhe and heady, but aduiſed and iuſt, intended for vnity and quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in the Church, to preuent and repreſſe
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:21468:14"/>phanaticall giddineſſe, ſchiſme, factions and innouation.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The Errours of this Argument, are aſwell the ſame with the former, as alſo <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; in the allegation of an impertinent Example.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="argument">
            <head>V. ARGVMENT.</head>
            <p>IT is not to be forgotten, with what courage and good ſucceſſe<note n="a)" place="margin">Impertinent Examples.</note>
               <hi>Nehemiah</hi> ſpake for the materiall Ieruſalem, to
<hi>Artaſhaſht</hi> an heathen and prophane King, <hi>Neh. 2.2. &amp;c.</hi> as alſo how moſt vertuous and noble <hi>Q. Eſther,</hi> beeing indeed prouoked by poore <hi>Mordecai,</hi> aduentured her ſelfe, to ſpeake to the like conditioned King <hi>Ahaſhueroſh,</hi> in behalfe of the old people of God the Iewes, for preuenting of their bodily bloodſhed, notwithſtanding ſhe had not <hi>beene called vnto the King in thirty dayes before, and notwithſtanding there were a lawe of the King, that whoſoeuer, man or woman ſhould come vnto the King in the inward Court, not called, ſhould die, except ſuch as to whom the King ſhould haue held forth his golden rod.</hi> It is not (I ſay) to be forgotten, but religiouſly to bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred, how notwithſtanding the foreſaid danger and her former feare and weakeneſſe in that reſpect, yet at the laſt ſhee promiſed
<hi>Mordecai</hi> to aduenture her ſelfe, ſaying, <hi>If I periſh, I periſh:</hi> and how alſo af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter prayer and faſting of her ſelfe &amp; her ladies, and of the reſt of the Iewes in <hi>Shuſhan</hi> for her, ſhe entered to the King and ſpake for her people: and what grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:21468:15"/>ſucceſſe ſhe had, notwithſtanding the power and might of their chiefe aduerſary, and his great grace and fauour with the king. Did theſe perſons ſo aduenture themſelues to ſpeake before ſuch Kings, and did the GOD of heauen giue ſuch gracious ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe in their attempts? And ſhall Chriſtian Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and Gentlemen nowe aſſembled in high Court of Parliament: where they may ſpeake, and other in other places of authority and grace and fauour with chriſtian Princes, feare to ſpeake for the<note n="b)" place="margin">Afoule beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of the Queſtion: as if the Schiſme of a few, were-ſo iuſt and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant a mat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter, as the deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uety of the whole church of God from intended cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</note> people of God, to a chriſtian King, whoſe education from the Cradle, in all piety, former raigne and gouernement, and religious profeſsion hitherto, do giue better incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement? God forbid. And far be al ſuch feare &amp; co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardlineſſe from all that profeſſe and know the Coſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell of Ieſus Chriſt. Yea if there be any ſo fearefull and cowardly, let them ſeriouſly conſider the ſecond words and meſſage of <hi>Mordecai</hi> to <hi>Eſter. Thinke not that thou ſhalt eſcape in the Kings houſe, more then all the Iewes: For if thou holdeſt thy peace at this time, comfort and deliuerance ſhall appeare to the Iewes out of another place, but thou and thy fathers houſe ſhall periſh. Who knoweth whether thou art come to the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, for ſuch a time. Eſter. 4.13.</hi> Let them (I ſay) wiſely and in the feare of God conſider this meſſage, to prouoke themſelues to the more zeale and chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian boldneſſe, with all humility and mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty. Let them not thinke that they by their great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe ſhall procure<note n="c)" place="margin">Theſe pure Angels of light, forſooth think all the world in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes beſides themſelues.</note> a better miniſtery of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell to themſelues and their houſes, then other haue.
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:21468:15"/>If it bee reſtrayned from other, as of late it<note n="d)" place="margin">An impude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vntruth of a falſe Prophet. They made themſelues vncapable of any place in the Miniſtery.</note> hath beene, they ſhall not long enioy more liberty thereof then other. Yea, if they at this time and in that place where there is ſuch freedome of ſpeech, hold their peace, and do not with al their gifts and graces of knowledge, wiſedome, zeale, compaſsion modeſty and humilitie, that may be, put forth them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in furtherance of the<note n="e)" place="margin">They meane their Presbitery &amp;c</note> ſincere miniſterie of the Goſpell and<note n="f)" place="margin">Note this. Theſe Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliants would haue all the Biſhops
<hi>remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued</hi> &amp; depri. priued.</note> remouing the lets and impediments thereof: ſurely helpe may come in theſe things vnto the Church by ſome other meanes, but let them take heede that the Lord of Hoſtes call them not to an accompt and other reckoning for this their feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe. Further to adde one other example briefely. If fearefull <hi>Ioſeph</hi> of
<hi>Arimathea</hi> went boldly to <hi>Pilate</hi> and aſked the body of
<hi>Ieſus:</hi> And if <hi>Nico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demus</hi> (before as fearefull as the ſaid
<hi>Ioſeph</hi>) ioyned with him in the honourable buriall thereof, (when Chriſt was dead, and the whole ſtate bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing enemies vnto him) had now preuailed and got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten that which long they had laboured for againſt him: yea, when all the <hi>Diſciples</hi> had forſaken him, and ſome of the chiefeſt Champions had denyed him, oh how diſhonourable with men and inexcuſable and vnanſwerable before God ſhall it bee, that ſo many hauing learned more of Chriſt then eyther <hi>Ioſeph</hi> and
<hi>Nicodemus,</hi> or all the <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples</hi> themſelues had then learned, and hauing alſo before boldly profeſſed and promiſed much for him, and liuing in a Kingdome<note n="g)" place="margin">If we <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe Chriſt &amp; maintaine his Goſpell</hi> what do they plead for then? And wherefore haue they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied it al this while, preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding they la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but <hi>the Goſpell &amp; mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery thereof.</hi>
               </note> profeſsing Chriſt &amp; maintayning his Goſpell, &amp; vnder a moſt gracious
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:21468:16"/>religious King, and beeing in place of freedome of ſpeech, and now alſo aſſembled chiefly and principally for that end: (for what are all ſtatutes for the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth, without regard of the Church) howe diſhonourable (I ſay) with men, and howe inexcuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and vnanſwerable before God and his Sonne Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, when he ſhall come to iudgement, ſhall it be, that ſuch perſons, in ſuch a kingdome, vnder ſuch a King, in ſuch a place, at ſuch a time, ſhall not dare to ſpeake for<note n="h" place="margin">Lo, now the Diſcipli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narian ataxie, for which the Suppliants plead ſo much is <hi>whole Chriſt I ſus!</hi> Intolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie.</note> whole Chriſt Ieſus, riſen againe from the dead aſcended into the heauens, there ſitting in all power, glory and maiesty? Yea finally beeing ready to come to iudge both the quicke and the dead, both men and Angells? Oh therfore, ye that lone this Lord Ieſus Chriſt, take heede of ſuch fearefulneſſe: yea, feare ſo to bee afraid of ſpeaking for him, for his Goſpell &amp; for his ſeruants.</p>
            <div type="resolution">
               <head>Reſolution of the 5. Argument.</head>
               <p>Many ſpake earneſtly: yea, and ſome haue aduentured their liues in behalfe of the Church of God, as Nehemiah, Heſter: ſo alſo did Ioſeph of Arimathea, and Nichodemus for Chriſts body.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ergo.</hi> So ſhould the high Court of Parliament doe, for the Refractary Miniſters, and for whole Chriſt.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="answer">
            <head>ANSWER.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>I. To the Antecedent.</head>
               <p>The zeale and courage of ſuch as haue beene earneſt, or aduentured their liues and eſtate in
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:21468:16"/>Gods cauſe, for defence of his eternall trueth and Church, is certainely much to be commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and imitated (to their vtmoſt power) of all ſuch as deſire to be called and be indeede mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Church of God. But it would bee wiſely coſidered, that it were raſhneſſe and foole-hardineſſe, for any to aduenture hazard, or manifeſt danger, by intermedling in a friuolous and vnneceſſarie quarel, and much more for ſuch cauſe as can not be iuſtified by any probable rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. Wherefore I anſwere</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>II. To the Conſequence</head>
               <p n="1">1. THis Conſequence hath no coherence with the Antecedent. For there are great ods betweene theſe examples propoſed and the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fractarie Miniſters caſe.</p>
               <p n="1">I. In the time of <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> the Church of the Iewes, having bin long captiuated, was <hi>in great affliction and reproach,</hi> and the <hi>walles of Ieruſalem</hi> were <hi>broken downe.</hi> (<hi>Nehem.</hi> 1.3.) which was not ſo in the dayes of their fathers. But our Church ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving (by the mercies of God) now long conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued in proſperous and flouriſhing eſtate, is (God be thanked) glorious ſtill, yea more now then e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer it was in the dayes of our fathers.</p>
               <p>Furthermore, <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> after he had <hi>wept, mourned, faſted and prayed</hi> (<hi>Nehem.</hi> 1.4.) ſpake vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to King
<hi>Artaſhaſte, an heathen and prophane man,</hi> and finding grace in his eyes, obtayned leaue to build vp Ieruſalem. (<hi>Nehem.</hi> 2.6.) But
<hi>Sanballat, Tobiah, Geſhem</hi> and others deriding
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:21468:17"/>and deſpiſing the Iewes, laboured to hinder the worke, but preuayled not (<hi>Nehem.</hi> 2.19. <hi>and</hi>
4.7.15.) Then <hi>Nehemiah</hi> prayed, <hi>My God, remember thou Tobiah and Sanballat, according vnto theſe their workes.</hi> (<hi>Nehem.</hi> 6.14.) So euen in the very beginning of our religious Soueraignes raigne, many worthy
<hi>Nehemiahs</hi> finding grace in his eyes, haue moued his Maieſtie for the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of the proſperous eſtate of our Church, as it was in dayes of our late bleſſed Queene, albeit his Highneſſe was more ready to graunt their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, then they to aſke it. And nowe, ſo many <hi>Sanballats, Tobiahs,</hi> and <hi>Geſhems,</hi> as there be Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fractarie: Miniſters and Papiſtes, deriding and deſpiſing vs, labour to hinder our Miniſtery, blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheming the ſame, either to be none at all, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulterate and very corrupt, but (Godwilling) ſhal not preuaile. And we ſtill thinking that moſt of them do ſinne of ignorance, ceaſe not to pray vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God: <hi>O Lord, open the eyes of theſe men, and lay not this ſinne to their charge.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>II.</hi> In the dayes of the noble and renowned <hi>Q. Heſter,</hi> all the Iewes ſhould haue bin ſwallowed vp by the manny of
<hi>Haman,</hi> had not that vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Queene, by aduenturing her owne life, deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered her people fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> deſtruction. But I hope the Suppliants do not thinke our Church to be in ſo deſperate a ſtate, neither outwardly, nor ſpiritual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. And if they do, yet none can be ſo fooliſh as to beleeue it.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>III.</hi> The examples of <hi>Ioſeph of Arimathea</hi> and <hi>Nicodemus</hi> are altogither impertinent: for neither had <hi>Pilate</hi> any reaſon to deny the buriall of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:21468:17"/>
                  <hi>Chriſts</hi> body being dead: nor is the Miniſters re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts concerning Croſſe, and Surplice any thing of ſuch importance, as was the buriall of Chriſts body. For it is not true that they contend about <hi>Whole Chriſt Ieſus, and the Miniſtery of the Goſpell,</hi> as the Suppliants here ſuggeſt.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Errour is threefold. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 2.
<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 3. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="argument">
            <head>VI. ARGVMENT.</head>
            <p>LEt the great heauineſſe of many<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mutato no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine de te Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bula narratur.</hi> The Refracta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie Miniſters ought to haue had compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on on theſe Sheepe, &amp; not deſperately haue forſaken the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for Croſſe and Surplice.</note> Congregations Men, Women, children, Maiſters and ſeruants, of all ages and conditions, be pitifully conſidered. God regarded the weeping of bond
<hi>Hagar,</hi> and reprobate <hi>Iſhmaell,</hi> in the want of the water of this life. <hi>Gen. 21.16.</hi> He graciouſly reſpected the poore women that complayning of the cruelty of their Husbands in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaking them, <hi>and vexing them</hi> by taking other wiues, <hi>had covered his Altar with their teares. Malac. 2.13.14.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Lord Ieſus alſo pitied the people. yea, his bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els yerned within him to ſee them ſcattered as ſheepe without a<note n="b" place="margin">Refractary Shepheards run away and forſake their flockes.</note> ſhepheard: <hi>Math. 9.36. Mark. 6.34</hi> Yea he did graciouſly reſpect the petitions of many touching the bodily miſeries of their children, friends and ſeruants, yea the ſutes of ſome for bodily com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of their children, though themſelues were not of the children of Iſraell but Heathen and Cananites &amp; little better in that reſpect then<note n="c" place="margin">Abſurd. The woman was ſuch as that Chriſt himſelf teſtified of her, that he <hi>had not found ſo great faith in Iſrael</hi> Read the place.</note> Dogges? <hi>Math: 15.12.</hi> How then ſhould the ſpirituall miſeries of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thouſands, partly already<note n="d" place="margin">And all by reaſon of the wilfulneſſe &amp; ſuperſtitious obſtinacy of the paſtors themſelues.</note> depriued, &amp; partly like
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:21468:18"/>to be depriued of their<note n="e)" place="margin">Oh, won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, that for ſake their flock in the plaine field.</note> faithfull Paſtors, who haue broken the bread, and powred out the water of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life vnto them, and performed the duties as it were of louing<note n="f)" place="margin">Onely Chriſt is the Hu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>band of his Spouſe. Here the Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliants blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemouſly papize. For I thinke they meane not this literally, if they do, they are (ſurely) very honeſt men in the meane time.</note> husbands, and who by ſuch Paſtors &amp; Preachers, <hi>haue beene turned from darkneſſe to light, and deliuered from the power of Sathan vnto God,</hi> and who now therefore in the want of them, doe<note n="g)" place="margin">A lying Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perbole.</note> couer the Lords Altar with teares, and make lamentable mone (as the <hi>Turtle Doue,</hi> that hath lost her mate) for helpe to themſelues &amp; theirs, against the preſent and future ſpirituall calamities: how I ſay ought all theſe things to wring, and wrest, pity and compaſsion<note n="h)" place="margin">If the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fractarie Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters be ſo vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind and hard harted, that they wil haue no pittie vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, they may be otherwiſe releeued well inough, <hi>See the Anſwere.</hi>
               </note> from all in auctority towards them? O therefore let not their mone and lamentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on be neglected.</p>
            <div type="resolution">
               <head>Reſolution of the 6. Argument.</head>
               <p>Many Congregations, Men, Women, Children, Maſters and Seruants, of all ages and conditions, are in great heauineſſe for their Paſtours, and do make lamentable moane for them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ergo:</hi> The States of the Parliament must needes be Suiters vnto his Maieſtie for reſtoring of them againe.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="answer">
            <head>ANSWER.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>I. To the Antecedent.</head>
               <p n="1">1. IF the Antecedent be true, as the Suppliants ſeeme confidently to affirme, then ſurely the more hard hearts haue thoſe cruell Tyrants, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then Shepheards, that hauing no pittie nor compaſſion vpon thoſe ſillie ſheepe, deſperately
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:21468:18"/>forſake their flockes, ouer whom the Lord had made them ouerſeers; and relinquiſh their vocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for little or no cauſe at all.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Thoſe <hi>Congregations, Men, Women, Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren &amp;c.</hi> may ceaſe to mourne any longer, and comfort themſelues herewith, <hi>viz.</hi> that ſeeing their vnfaithfull and vngratefull Paſtours haue dealt ſo vnkindly and vndutifully with them; yet (God be thanked) the Lord hath ſtore of good and faithfull Seruants, which he will ſend forth into the Harueſt, who both can and will <hi>breake the bread, and poure out the water of eternall life vnto them,</hi> and performe the duties of faithfull Shepheards, that will neuer forſake them, nor runne away when they haue moſt need of their helpe,</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>II.</hi> To the Conſequence.</head>
               <p n="1">
                  <hi>1. The Conſequence followeth not from the Antecedent, but this rather: Ergo,</hi> The Paſtours must needs haue pitty vpon their miſerable diſtreſſe, and obeying the wholeſome ordinances of the Church, returne againe and comfort them.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2. The Errour is,</hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="argument">
            <head>VII. ARGVMENT.</head>
            <p>TO regard theſe Miniſters hitherto ſpoken of, is to regard the<note n="a)" place="margin">Is a handful of Refractarie Miniſters the ſafetie of the <hi>whole land?</hi>
               </note> whole land. For it is not to be doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, but that it may be ſpoken of them, as well as of ſome other, that, <hi>they are the Chariots and Horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of England,</hi> as the like is acknowledged for Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raell, not onely of <hi>Elia</hi> by <hi>Eliſha,
2.</hi> King. <hi>2.12.</hi> but alſo
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:21468:19"/>of <hi>Eliſha</hi> by <hi>Ioaſh</hi> a wicked King of Iſrael, <hi>2 King. 13.14. If God be with vs, who can be againſt vs, Rom 8.31.</hi> And if the <hi>Almightie be our defence</hi> (as
<hi>Eliphas</hi> ſpeaketh to <hi>Iob,</hi> Iob <hi>22.25.</hi>) We cannot but be in peace and ſafety.</p>
            <p>Now God hath not promiſed to be with any for their defence, but ſuch as<note n="b)" place="margin">As if God never had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended any
<hi>Pagan</hi> in caſe of Iuſtice and Innocencie. But ſet this paſſe as im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent to our queſtion.</note> receiue his Goſpell. In the Miniſtery alſo of the Goſpell, conſiſteth the wealth and honor of every people, <hi>Pro. 3.16. Pſa. 46.12.</hi> And the glory of every kingdome, as the glory of Iſraell did in the <hi>Arke. 1. Sam. 4.21.22.</hi> And the peace of Nations. For therefore, as well as for other reſpects, the Goſpell is called the Goſpel of peace, <hi>Eph. 6.15.</hi> compared with
<hi>Iſai. 2.4.</hi> and <hi>11.6.</hi> and <hi>65.25.</hi> Finally, the whole<note n="c)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Outward proſperitie co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth in pure worſhip.</hi> They ſpeake ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foundly, as an intelligent &amp; ſenſible man cannot vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand them. As if the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly flouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed not of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes <hi>as a greene Bay tree,</hi> and the <hi>outward proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peritie</hi> of the Perſians, and Romanes did not ſurpaſſe the meane e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate of the Iewes, the true Church of God.</note> out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward proſperity of all Kings and kingdomes conſiſteth principally in the pure worſhip of God, and the meanes that commends the ſame <hi>2. Chro
14.14.17.10.27. 6.24.26. 2. King. 18.7.</hi> Therefore they cannot be faithfull to Kings &amp; kingdoms, neither to themſelues that<note n="d)" place="margin">This ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be applied vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our ſtate. Let the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fractarie facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on looke into themſelues, that they do not thus, in forſaking their calling &amp; vocation.</note> neglect the true worſhip of God, and the meanes thereof. Therefore alſo, as <hi>Eſter</hi> ſaid of thoſe that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked <hi>Ahaſhueroſh</hi> againſt the Iewes, ſo may it be ſaid of all thoſe that perſwade the ſuppreſsion of the Goſpel, &amp; of the Miniſters thereof, <hi>Such aduerſaries cannot recompence the Kings loſſe.</hi> Eſter, <hi>7.4.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If therefore yee will not reſpect the ſtate of Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, their wiues &amp; children, yet reſpect your ſelues, your wiues and children, yea, our King and whole kingdome, even touching the outward eſtate of your ſelues and yours, of King and kingdome. And if yee loue the ſafetie, peace, wealth, and glory of King and Kingdome, and of your ſelues and yours, then ſpeake
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:21468:19"/>and do, what you all, and euery one of you may, for the<note n="e)" place="margin">What is this <hi>ad Rhombum?</hi> So they will, though you had neuer ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited them vnto it.</note> Goſpell and miniſtery thereof.</p>
            <div type="resolution">
               <head>Reſolution of the 7. Argument.</head>
               <p>To regard the Refractarie Miniſters, is to regard the whole land, the States of Parliament, their wiues and children, the King and Kingdome.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ergo.</hi> If the high Court of Parliament loue the ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, peace wealth, and glorie of King and Kingdom, and of themſelues and theirs, they must ſpeake and do what they may, for the Goſpell and Miniſterie thereof.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="answer">
            <head>ANSWER.</head>
            <p n="1">1. What can a ſenſible man make of this En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thymeme?
<hi>The Refractarie Miniſters are the ſafetie of the whole land.</hi> Ergo;
<hi>The Court of Parliament must ſpeake for the Goſpell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The Antecede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t is very improbable, if not alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether falſe; both becauſe there be thouſands of Godly, faithfull Miniſters in this kingdom, which are not of their faction, that are as <hi>Charets</hi> &amp; <hi>Horſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men:</hi> and alſo becauſe the Miniſters are therefore termed <hi>Charets and Horſemen,</hi> becauſe they are Gods inſtruments for gathering of his Saints by the exerciſe of their Miniſterie. But theſe men re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to exerciſe their Miniſterie, they have relin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhed and forſaken their calling; wherefore they can by no reaſon be termed <hi>Charets</hi> &amp; <hi>Horſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi> And ſo farre are they from being <hi>the ſafetie of the Land,</hi> that would God they were not the Sores of the Church, and Sowers of Sedition, I meane, Schiſme and Faction.</p>
            <p n="3">3. For the Conſequence, I am ſure it is from
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:21468:20"/>a Topique place called <hi>A baculo ad angulum,</hi> from the Staffe to the corner, for it hath not the leaſt coherence with the Antecedent, except the Suppliants meane that theſe wordes,
<hi>Refract arie Miniſters, the Goſpel, the Miniſterie of the Goſpel,</hi> be conuertible termes: which were abſurd and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The Errour is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="argument">
            <head>IIX. ARGVMENT.</head>
            <p>IT is the duety of all Princes and Magiſtrates, and alſo of their Courtes, <hi>to execute</hi>
               <note n="a)" place="margin">If
<hi>Iuſtice</hi> be executed, how can Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes looke for any fauour then? How well they plead for themſelues.</note> 
               <hi>iuſtice &amp; iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the morning, &amp; to deliuer the oppreſſed &amp;c. Ier.
21.12.22.2.</hi> eſpecially to do iuſtice towards the ſoules of men. Therefore this eſpecially doth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to this high Court of Parliament, as being the higheſt Court we haue for iuſtice and iudgment vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on earth. As Abraham therefore ſaid vnto God, <hi>Shall not the Iudge of all the world doe right Gen. 18.25.</hi> ſo ſay I to this preſent Court, ſhal not the higheſt Court of all this Kingdome doe right? Yea, this is the more at this preſent to bee conſidered, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe this iuſtice that nowe I ſpeake of, is not onely the Iuſtice of God, but alſo of this Land. For it is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundantly of late<note n="b)" place="margin">By whome?</note> proued, that all the late procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinges, againſt the miniſters, in repreſſing of their miniſtery, and in depriving them of their free holds, is<note n="c)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Moſt falſe.</hi> See the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere.</note> contrary to the lawes of this kingdome, both to <hi>Charta Magna,</hi> and alſo to many ſtatutes.</p>
            <p>The ſame is to be vnderſtood of the<note n="d)" place="margin">Obiect a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt theſe, and you ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be anſwered.</note> oath <hi>ex officio</hi> of many of the late Canons, &amp; of diuers other things.
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:21468:20"/>It is alſo againſt<note n="a)" place="margin">Theſe men would bring all things to popular trial.</note> reaſon, that the baſeſt Cobler and Tinker cannot bee eiected from his free hold of but ten ſhillings by the yeare, but by a Iury of <hi>12.</hi> men, and before ſome of his Maieſties Iudges in ſolemne forme of lawe, and<note n="b)" place="margin">
                  <hi>A ſenſeleſſe ſentence. How can a man</hi> in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of eternall life be caſt out of his free-hold?</note> that the miniſters &amp; Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors of Chriſt Ieſus, in the matters of eternall life, ſhould bee caſt out of their free hold, of what worth ſoeuer, by one man onely, and not onely without any Iury, but alſo<note n="c)" place="margin">The Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical Iudge may proceede <hi>Ex officio.</hi>
               </note> without any complaint or accuſation againſt them.</p>
            <p>If it be obiected that this that I haue ſaid, to be the iuſtice of this Kingdome, is but the<note n="d)" place="margin">Directly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Statute of. 1. <hi>Eliza.</hi> c. 2.</note> opinion of ſome priuate perſons: Let the miniſters finde fauour with this high Court of iuſtice, to haue the former cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes in the ſaid Court debated, as many the like haue beene heeretofore and dayly are. Shall priuat cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes be reſpected by you: yea ſhall matters of pouruey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors and ſuch like, of ſmall moment for the common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, come before you, and bee ſo largely diſcuſſed and handeled by you, and ſhall not ſo many publique cauſes, of ſo many, of ſuch quality, &amp; for the<note n="e)" place="margin">Begging of the Queſtion.</note> Church, be regarded? yea not the cauſe of GOD himſelfe? Shall GOD and his ſonne Chriſt Ieſus, in the cauſe of his Goſpell and miniſters thereof, ſtand as is were at your Parliament houſe<note n="f)" place="margin">As if they were not Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident of that Religious Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy. An vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtion.</note> dore knocking, and cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving to be let in, and to haue their cauſe heard, and ſhall not your dore be opened? Beware of this, leaſt ye knock alſo at heaven dore, and there be none found to open, or to anſwere vnto you.</p>
            <div type="resolution">
               <head>Reſolution of the. 8. Argument.</head>
               <p>The Magiſtrate ought to execute iuſtice and iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:21468:21"/>and to deliuer the oppreſſed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ergo.</hi> Much more ought the high Courte of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to do ſo, and to deliuer the Refractarie Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="answer">
            <head>ANSWER.</head>
            <p>I Am conſtrayned to dance, as the Suppliants pleaſe to pipe. They lead, and I follow. Hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to they prayed your Honours, but to
<hi>Speake</hi> for them vnto his excellent Maieſtie: which Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition they haue laboured to inforce by ſundrie Arguments, but how happily &amp; with what ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, your wiſdome can beſt iudge. Now they vrge, that it would pleaſe your Honorable Court to <hi>Determine</hi> ſomewhat in their behalfe, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually to <hi>Decree,</hi> that they may bee reſtored and not farther moleſted, how ſingularly or factiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſoeuer they ſhal behaue themſelues in their pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. Neither wil I reproue my Brethren, for diſloi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al preſumption in ſolliciting your Honorable aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly, abſolutely to <hi>Determine</hi> any thing herein, which they know his Maieſty wil not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deſcend vnto, ſeeing it may be they comprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe vnder the generall terme of <hi>Court of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> but wil I briefly anſwere the Argument.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To the Conſequence.</head>
               <p n="1">1. The Conſequence hath two parts. <hi>I. That the Honorable Court of Parliament is to execute Iuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice &amp; Iudgement,</hi> which I gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. <hi>Il. That they ought to deliuer &amp; reſtore the Refractary Miniſters.</hi> That reſtes to bee proved ſtil: becauſe they haue not yet iuſtified their cauſe, and declared that they are vniuſtly oppreſſed, nor can euer doe.</p>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:21468:21"/>
               <p>The Suppliants inſtance. <hi>It is abundantly of late proued, that all the late proceedings against Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, in repreſſing of their Miniſtery, and in depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing them of their free-holdes, is contrary to the Lawes of this kingdom, both to</hi> Charta Magna, <hi>and alſo to many ſtatutes. The ſame is to be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstood of the Oath</hi> ex Officio, <hi>of many of the late Canons, and other things.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I anſwer. 1. Touching him, that the Suppliants ſay, hath of late ſo abundantely proved the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfulnes of the proceedings againſt the Refrac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary Miniſters, I am out of doubt,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fractarie Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters.</hi> VVhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priuation of them be war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantably by lawe.</note> he is no Iudge, nor yet any good Civilian or Common Lawier. But howe ſufficiently hee hath performed that worke, it ſhall (God willing) ſhortly appeare.</p>
               <p n="2">2. In the meane time I would propound two or three Queſtions vnto the Suppliants, or their <hi>Late aboundant Probator,</hi> wherein I would craue their Reſolution, and direct Anſwer.</p>
               <p n="1">I. Quaere. <hi>Whether the Church vnder Chriſtian Godly Magistrats, hath any Tribunal proper vnto it ſelfe, for deciding of Controuerſies, and puniſhing of ſuch perſons, as ſhal refuſe the ordinances thereof?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">II. Quaere. <hi>Whether ſo many iudiciall Acts of depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of Biſhops, Prieſtes, Miniſters from their Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefices &amp;c. ſince the Conqueſt to the time of</hi> Magna Charta, <hi>and ſithence that to this age, were ever held to be contrarie to the Lawes of this Kingdome, and</hi> Magna Charta?</p>
               <p n="3">III. Quaere. <hi>Whether any Iudge of this Realme, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny chiefe officer learned in the Lawes, bee of opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, that ſuch Sentences of Deprivation,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:21468:22"/>as haue lately paſſed in due forme in any Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall Court, be contrarie to any, much leſſe, to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Statutes?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">
                  <note place="margin">A place of <hi>Magna Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta,</hi> alleadged by the Suppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ants, cleered.</note>3. But howſoeuer the Suppliants pretend <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> (<hi>cap.</hi> 29. for this is the place they aime at, as I thinke) where it is ſaid, <hi>No free man ſhall be taken or impriſoned, or be diſſeiſed of his free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold or liberties</hi> &amp;c.
<hi>We ſhall not paſſe vpon him nor condemne him, but by lawfull Iudgement of his Peeres, or by the law of the Land:</hi> Who, hauing but halfe an eye, doth not euidently ſee, that they would not onely weaken, but alſo ſubuert and vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly ouerthrow, the whole <hi>Iuriſdiction Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call,</hi> the Sentences and grave Determinations whereof were neuer yet in any age or Countrie ſubmitted to popular triall, by the
<hi>Iudgement of Peeres,</hi> that is, by a Iurie: as indeed their new Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline and Presbyterie cannot ſtand, but by ſuch popular triall and aſſiſtance.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Yet I anſwer. I. The place of <hi>Magna Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta</hi> cannot be vnderſtood of <hi>Eccleſiaſticall Iuriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction,</hi> or the practiſe thereof: ſpecially if we conſider the End, why that law was made; or the Time when. The End was this, that the Kings of this Realme ſhould not challenge an infinite and abſolute power to themſelues (as ſome Kings elſewhere did, and yet do) without iudgement and lawfull proceeding, to take away any mans <hi>libertie, life, countrie, goods</hi> or
<hi>lands.</hi> And it was at ſuch Time, when the Kings themſelues thought, that <hi>Iuriſdiction Eccleſiaſticall</hi> was not in right, no more then it was in fact at that time, belonging
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:21468:22"/>vnto the Crowne: therefore in that it is there ſaid, <hi>We will not paſſe vpon him, nor condemne him, but by lawfull iudgement of his Peeres, or by the law of the land;</hi> it is manifeſt, that the words haue no relation to <hi>Iuriſdiction Eccleſiaſticall:</hi> for that which was done by that
<hi>Iuriſdiction,</hi> was not at that time taken to be done by the King, or by his Auctoritie: and the lawes which <hi>Eccleſiaſticall Iudges</hi> practiſed, were not then held to be the <hi>Lawes of the Land,</hi> or the
<hi>Kings lawes;</hi> as (ſince the lawfull and neceſſarie reſtitution of the ancient Right in that behalfe to the Crowne) they be of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten called,
<hi>the Kings</hi> or <hi>Queenes Eccleſiaſticall lawes.</hi> 1.
<hi>Elizab. cap.</hi> 2. <hi>&amp; alibi paſsim.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <note place="margin">Biſhops may Deprive &amp;c.</note>II. As Inſtitution vnto a Benefice, both be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore and after <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> belonged alwayes to <hi>Eccleſiaſticall Perſons</hi> and
<hi>Iuriſdiction;</hi> ſo did alſo the Deſtitution or Deprivation of a Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice by the Common law: for, <hi>Cuius est inſtituere, eius est deſtituere.</hi> In which reſpect, Biſhops (that claime not the patronage) do alwayes plead to a <hi>Quare impedit,</hi> thus, <hi>Nihil clamat praeter Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutionem &amp; Deſtitutionem Clericorum, vt Ordinari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us &amp;c.</hi> Whereby may appeare, that a man might (by law) be put out of his Benefice (being his <hi>freehold</hi>) otherwiſe then according vnto the forme of that Statute.</p>
               <p n="3">III. An Ordinarie in his Dioceſſe (even at the Common law) might and may <hi>Condemne</hi> a man for Hereſie, wherevpon (being committed to Secular power) ſuch an Heretique was put to death. But this was not done <hi>by Iudgement of his
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:21468:23"/>Peeres,</hi> and therefore thoſe words of
<hi>Magna Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta,</hi> are no way to be vnderſtood of
<hi>Eccleſiaſticall Iuriſdiction.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">IV. Beſides the <hi>Iudgement of a mans Peeres,</hi> there is added, <hi>Or by the law of the land;</hi> which permitteth other triall, then by <hi>Peeres;</hi> as by <hi>Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">V. And now ſeeing all Iuriſdiction and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctoritie in this Realme, aſwell <hi>Eccleſiaſticall,</hi> as <hi>Temporall,</hi> was euer in right, but now is abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly acknowledged, and is in fact, vnited and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corporated vnto the Crowne of this Realme: therefore that iudgement that is duely giuen by the <hi>Iuriſdiction Eccleſiaſticall,</hi> is given by the <hi>Law of the Land;</hi> and ſo not contrarie vnto <hi>Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na Charta.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. As touching thoſe <hi>Many other Statutes,</hi> if the Suppliants had alleadged or pointed at them, they ſhould have receaved their Anſwer in like maner.</p>
               <p n="6">
                  <note place="margin">Deprivation adiudged lawfull.</note>6. Briefly, the lawfulneſſe of the <hi>Deprivation</hi> of the Refractarie Miniſters, is a plaine caſe ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudged in open Court, as appeareth in
<hi>Sir Edward Cookes Reports, part.</hi> 5. <hi>in Caudreies Caſe:</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vnto a Statute of 1. <hi>Elizab. cap.</hi> 2. in theſe words.
<hi>Be it ordained and enacted by the Auctori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie aforeſaid, that all and ſingular Archbiſhops and Biſhops, and every of their Chancellours, Commiſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, Archdeacons and other Ordinaries, having any peculiar Iuriſdiction Eccleſiaſticall, ſhall have full power and auctoritie by vertue of this Acte, aſwell to enquire,</hi> (which they may do <hi>ex Officio</hi>) <hi>in their
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:21468:23"/>viſitations, Synods and elſewhere, within their Iuriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, at any other time or place, to take accuſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and informations of all and of every the things above mentioned</hi> (touching the Booke of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon prayer &amp;c.) <hi>done, committed or perpetrated, within the limits of their Iuriſdictions and auctori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and to puniſh the ſame by admonition, excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication, ſequeſtration or DEPRIVATION, and other cenſures and proceſſe, in like forme as hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hath beene vſed in like caſes by the Queenes Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall Lawes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. Concerning the <hi>Oath ex Officio, and many of the late Canons, and other things;</hi> if the Suppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ants had obiected any thing againſt them, they ſhould haue beene conſidered. <hi>Eadem enim facili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate reijcitur, quod ſine ratione affirmatur.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="8">8. The Errour is, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. And
<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="9" type="argument">
            <head>IX. ARGVMENT.</head>
            <p>MAy it further pleaſe them to whom this preſent writing is directed, to call to minde the promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes made to them, that ſhew any kindneſſe to any of the Children of God, and diſciples of Christ, eſpecially to any <hi>Prophet in the name of a Prophet,</hi> Mat.
<hi>10.41.</hi> As alſo to conſider, <hi>that God is not vnrighteous, that he ſhould forget ſuch workes and labour of loue.</hi> Heb. <hi>6.10.</hi> but that <hi>he is faithful that hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed.</hi> Heb. <hi>10.23.</hi> and that <hi>God is not as man, that he ſhould lie, neither as the ſonne of man, that he ſhould repent: hath he ſaid it, &amp; ſhal not he do it? and hath he ſpoken, &amp; ſhall not he accompliſh it?</hi> Num.
<hi>23.19.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:21468:24"/>
            <p>He that made <hi>Saule,</hi> (though vnnatural to his own children, <hi>1. Sam. 14.49.</hi> and a cruell murderer of the Prieſts of the Lord. <hi>1. Sam. 22.18.</hi>) to ſhew mercy to the <hi>Kenits,</hi> (as it were the Rocke to yeeld wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter). <hi>1. Sam. 15.6.</hi> for the kindneſſe of <hi>Iethro,</hi> (otherwiſe called <hi>Keni,</hi> Iudg. <hi>1.16.</hi>) towards the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> in giuing onely good counſell to
<hi>Moſes,</hi> for the better outward governme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the <hi>Iſraelites,
400.</hi> yeares before. <hi>Exod. 18.17.</hi> Shall he forget, the kindneſſe that ſhall bee ſhewed to the<note n="a)" place="margin">Miniſters are to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded, as they be ſuch, and in their Office: but not as they be ſchiſmatikes and diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the peace of the Church.</note> Miniſters of the Goſpell, and to the people committed vnto them, and depending vpon them, for the foode and ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their ſoules?</p>
            <p>Was the kindneſſe of the <hi>Shunamite,</hi> towards one prophet <hi>Eliſha,</hi> plentifully recompenced, <hi>1.</hi> by the gift of a Sonne after long barrennes, <hi>2.</hi> by reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring her ſaid ſonne to life being dead, <hi>2. Kings. 4.16.3.</hi> by forewarning her of a famine to come, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhing her, to provide for her ſelfe <hi>Chap. 8.1.4.</hi> by directing her, by God his gratious providence, to come with petition to the
<hi>King,</hi> for reſtitution of her lands (that had beene ſeiſed in her abſence to the kings vſe) at that very inſtant, when <hi>Gehazi</hi> was telling the King the great acts of his <hi>M. Eliſha,</hi> and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly how he had raiſed this womans ſon fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> death to life: (by which her comming in ſuch a ſeaſon ſhee preſently obtayned, not only her lands, but alſo al the meane profites that in time of her peregrination, had beene taken by the Kings receiver:) was (I ſay) ſuch little kindneſſe of this woman, to one prophet, ſo plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully recompenſed, and ſhall not the favour that is ſhewed to many Miniſters of the Goſpell, (the leaſt
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:21468:24"/>wherof, for<note n="b)" place="margin">Arcadian wiſdom: The place is to be vnderſtood, not in regard of the
<hi>Office,</hi> but in reſpect of the cleare knowledge that they ſhould haue of Chriſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection.</note> office is greater then
<hi>Iohn</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt,</hi> who notwithſtanding was greater then any prophet, and then whom there was not a greater, among the ſonnes begotten of women, <hi>(Math. 11.9.)</hi> ſhall not (I ſay) ſuch kindneſſe towards ſuch Miniſters as are in<note n="c)" place="margin">How
<hi>great,</hi> I pray you?</note> ſo great reckoning with God, be remembred and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded?</p>
            <div type="resolution">
               <head>Reſolution of the 9. Argument.</head>
               <p>God doth ever plentifully recompence any kindneſſe ſhewed vnto his Children, ſpecially vnto the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and Diſciples of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ergo:</hi> The high Court of Parliament ought to ſhew kindneſſe vnto the Refractarie Miniſters.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="answer">
            <head>ANSWER.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To the Conſequence.</head>
               <p n="1">1. OVr Sauiour ſaith, <hi>He that receiueth a Prophet, in the name of a Prophet, ſhall receiue a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets reward.</hi> (<hi>Math.</hi> 10.41.) So ſhall he alſo that doth any kindneſſe vnto a Miniſter, as he is a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter. But if a Miniſter do otherwiſe then he ought, (as theſe Refractaries do) what kindneſſe then ought ſuch to haue done vnto them?</p>
               <p n="2">2. Let the Refractarie Miniſters dutifully ſerue GOD and his Church, in their diligent and hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble obedience, in the worke of their vocation, and then let them ſupplicate for kindneſſe to be ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vnto them.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The Errour is, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="10" type="argument">
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:21468:25"/>
            <head>X. ARGVMENT.</head>
            <p>ON the contrary conſider, who hath ſaid, <hi>Touch not mine annointed, and doe</hi>
               <note n="a)" place="margin">Well <hi>My Prophets,</hi> not falſe or ſchiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticall Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets.</note> 
               <hi>my Prophets no harme:</hi> Pſal. <hi>105.15.</hi> As alſo what is threatned to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that doe the leaſt harme to the least of the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of God, even in their outward ſtates. Yea, what God commanded to be written againſt the
<hi>Amalekites,</hi> &amp; ſware to performe, onely for reſisting his people, in their iourney towards the earthly <hi>Canaan,</hi> which was but a type of the heavenly. <hi>Exod. 17.14.15.</hi> And what alſo afterward (even
<hi>400.</hi> yeares after the premiſes) he cauſed to be executed by
<hi>Saule</hi> against them, <hi>without any pity or compaſſion, towards any man, woman, infant, or ſuckling, Oxe, Sheep, Cattell, or Aſſe,
1.</hi> Sam. <hi>15.3.</hi> Was it ſo hainous before the Lord, to hinder his people in their iourney towards the earthly <hi>Canaan,</hi> and ſhall it be a light thing with men now, not to<note n="b)" place="margin">They ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be ſaid to far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>the Elect,</hi> that wilfully forſake the Miniſtery of the Goſpel, as the Refracta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryes do.</note> further the elect in their meanes of, and in their iourney vnto the heavenly <hi>Canaan,</hi> typically prefigured, <hi>by that earthly?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If the Lord did alſo ſweare, <hi>by the excellencie of</hi> Iacob, <hi>that ſurely he would never forget the cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, that was exerciſed by the rich men of</hi> Iudea, <hi>againſt the poore of the land, in their outward ſtate: yea, that the very land ſhould tremble, and that every one ſhould mourne that dwelled ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in &amp;c. for the ſaid ſinne.</hi> Amos <hi>8.7.</hi> Will the ſame Lord then, which is alwayes the ſame in Iuſtice, as well as in mercy, lightly paſſe by any<note n="c)" place="margin">They may be ſaid to bee <hi>Cruel towards the ſoules of m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> that for little or no cauſe, leaue then diligent and honeſt calling in the Miniſtery of the Goſpell.</note> cruelty towards the ſoules of his people?</p>
            <p>Let not the ſtates aſſembled in this High Court of
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:21468:25"/>Parliament, or in any place of auctoritie, grace, and fauour, where their word ſpoken in his place, <hi>may be like vnto Apples of golde, with pictures of ſilver, Pro. 25.11.</hi> Let them not (I ſay) waſh their hands off this argument becauſe they haue no hand in any<note n="d)" place="margin">You ſhould firſt haue pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the
<hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull.</note> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding against the Miniſters, or in reſtraining of their miniſtery ſith it is all one ſo to proceed &amp;c. and not to helpe them that are ſo proceeded against by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, eſpecially when power is in their hands to helpe. For it must never be forgotten, which is written for an everlaſting truth, and a perpetuall inſtruction, <hi>Curſe yee</hi> Meroz <hi>(ſaid the Angell of the Lord) curſe the inhabitants thereof, becauſe they came not to helpe the Lord, to helpe the Lord againſt the mightie, Iudges 5.23.</hi> In which place this is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe worthy the obſeruation of all men, that they are eſteemed not to helpe the Lord, that came not out to helpe his people. If there were ſo fearefull a curſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced by the Angell of the Lord againſt them that did not helpe his people, againſt the mightie enemies of their outward ſtate, may they thinke themſelues ſecure and without danger, that helpe not the<note n="e)" place="margin">Stil they beg the Queſtion.</note> Lord and his people, againſt the mighty that oppugne the everlaſting ſaluation of their ſoules?</p>
            <div type="resolution">
               <head>Reſolution of the 10. Argument.</head>
               <p>God threatneth ſeverely to puniſh the wrongs &amp; iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries done vnto his children and Servants, euen in their outward ſtates; much more the crueltie to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards their ſoules.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ergo:</hi> The high Court of Parliament ſhould neither proceed ſo hardly against the Miniſters, nor winke at others that do ſo proceed.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="answer">
            <pb n="56" facs="tcp:21468:26"/>
            <head>
               <hi>ANSWER.</hi> To the Conſequence.</head>
            <p n="1">1. NEither did the Honorable Court of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, nor the Magiſtrates of this Land, ever intend the leaſt wrong to any Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect in this kingdome, much leſſe to any of the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the Goſpel,</hi> no not in their outward eſtate, much leſſe towards the ſalvation <hi>of the peoples ſoules.</hi> And certainly it is an vngrateful, yea an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratious part of theſe Supplia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, to taxe that Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable Aſſembly, or any Magiſtrate in this land, ſo vndutifully and vnchriſtianly, for vniuſt, cruell and mercileſſe dealing.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Refractarie Miniſters were never <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded against for preaching the Goſpel,</hi> or for oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune and ſober executing their Miniſteriall func<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: but onely for giddie innovation and novel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, for faction, ſchiſme and impugning the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates auctority, or diſturbing the peace and quietneſſe of the Church. And would they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt theſe vile enormities to be left vnpuniſhed? An vnreaſonable Suite.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Errour is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Alſo,
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,</p>
         </div>
         <div n="11" type="argument">
            <head>XI. ARGRMENT.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>PHarao</hi> in the time of dearth, provided at his owne coſt for the Idolatrous Prieſts of <hi>Egypt,</hi> that they might not ſel their land: <hi>Gen. 47.22.</hi> Shall
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:21468:26"/>then ſo Chriſtian a kingdome, as this long time hath beene in the time of plenty, proceede ſo hardly againſt the painfull miniſters of the Goſpell, that they, their<note n="a)" place="margin">Where Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth Iudge, there neither Nature, nor Reaſon may dare to pleade the Cauſe. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las! It is very lamentable, that ſome men (I knowe not for what carnall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects) had rather currie fauour with others and be beholding vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to other men, then conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onably liue of their owne. They ſhould well conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſaying of the Apoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle. 1. Tim. 5.8.</note> wiues and children ſhall weepe and mourne for want? And will no man open his mouth in their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe? Were the <hi>Monks</hi> and
<hi>Friers</hi> at the diſſolution of their Idolatrous houſes, (in the twilight of the Goſpel,) provided for during their liues, though they neuer had done any good? And ſhall the miniſters of the Goſpell that haue converted many to God, and ſpent themſelues, and waſted their patrimony, firſt, in fitting the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues for the worke of the miniſtery, &amp; af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter by their ſufferings and troubles, ſo that they haue nothing left for their comfort in their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ge, be<note n="b)" place="margin">Alas! Let them haue pittie vpon themſelues, and leaue their quarel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and they ſhall not be neglected.</note> neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected? Though this hath not beene regarded, by thoſe that deprived them: yet farre bee it from this moſt Honorable Court, that any heart would bee found therein ſo hard and ſtony, as not with commi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeration to pity them.</p>
            <div type="resolution">
               <head>Reſolution of the .XI. Argument.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pharao</hi> prouided for the Idolatrous Prieſtes of Egypt. And the Monkes and Friers at the diſſolution of their Idolatrous Houſes, were prouided for during their liues, though they never had doone any good.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ergo.</hi> Much more ought the Refractarie Miniſters be provided for, hauing doone ſo great good in the Church of God.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="answer">
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:21468:27"/>
            <head>
               <hi>ANSWER.</hi> To the Conſequence.</head>
            <p n="1">1. THe Argument doth not follow, becauſe of the diſſimilitude that is in the inſtances or examples and the Miniſters cauſe.</p>
            <p n="1">I. <hi>Pharao</hi> miniſtred dayly Foode vnto ſuch Prieſtes, as he thought profeſſed true Religion, and diligently obeyed him in the function of their Office. A rate example of a bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiful &amp; mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificent Prince, though otherwiſe in Errour.</p>
            <p>But the Refractary Miniſters, though profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing true Religion, yet do they obſtinately, being blinded by Superſtition, refuſe to ſerue GOD &amp; his Church in the faithfull and diligent function and exerciſe of their Miniſtery.</p>
            <p n="2">II. The <hi>Monkes</hi> and <hi>Friers</hi> were depriued of al, againſt their will, for Sodomie, Hereſie and Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry, which they had embraced in time of their ignorance.</p>
            <p>But the Refractary Miniſters are willingly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priued, for obſtinate Superſtition, in refuſing ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely to preach the Goſpel of Chriſt with vs, not being conformable vnto the Chriſtian lawes of our Church and Magiſtrate.</p>
            <p n="3">III. The <hi>Monkes</hi> and <hi>Friers</hi> could not haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned their places and poſſeſſions, no not by ſubmitting themſelues: But the Refractarie Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters may, if they will but conforme themſelues vnto the lawfull ordinances of our Church.</p>
            <p n="2">2. For the <hi>Good</hi> which the Refractary Miniſters haue doone in the Church of GOD, I will no
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:21468:27"/>way extenuate their deſerts. but could haue wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that they had made greater co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience of their Miniſtery, wherby they might haue done <hi>more Good</hi> ſtill: and not like
<hi>Ephraemites,</hi> haue tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned their backes in the day of Battaile.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Errour is, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. And,
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="12" type="argument">
            <head>XII. ARGVMENT.</head>
            <p>MVch alſo may the prayers of ſuch miniſters, for this Court of Parliament, and for every ſtate and degree thereof, and for other, be<note n="a)" place="margin">True: if they continue dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent in their vocation. But being me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers rent and cut from the body of the Church of God in this land they are vnſeruiceable for the ſame.</note> regarded: <hi>for the prayer of the righteous availeth much, if it be fervent, Iames 5.16.</hi> And the prayers of the Saints are compared <hi>to Harpes and golden vialls full of odours &amp;c. Apoc. 5.8.</hi> God would haue <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bimelech King of Gerar,</hi> to make ſuch accompt of this argument, that for the ſame he would haue him <hi>to vſe Abraham the better, Gen. 20.7.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Neither did the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> onely, for this cauſe, moſt earneſtly craue the prayers of the meaneſt Chriſtians, in thoſe Churches to which hee wrote: b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lſo wicked
<hi>Pharao</hi> did earneſtly deſire the pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of <hi>Moſes and Aaron, Exod. 8.8. Darius</hi> alſo, though an heathen King, did therefore com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund all things neceſſary for the building of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> to bee aboundantly miniſtred to the Iewes, that they might <hi>pray for the Kings life, and for his ſonnes, Ezra. 6.10.</hi> Howe much more then ought ſuch Chriſtian aſſemblies as this preſent Highe Court of Parliament is, to labour the more,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:21468:28"/>for the comfort of God his children, eſpecially his<note n="b" place="margin">Are they <hi>Faithfull,</hi> that fall from their rule and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience?</note> faithfull miniſters, that thereby they may be incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged to prayer, the more earneſtly, for them and theirs.</p>
            <div type="resolution">
               <head>Reſolution of the 12. Argument.</head>
               <p>The Prayers of faithfull miniſters of the Goſpell, are very effectuall in behalfe of Chriſtian Aſſemblies.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ergo:</hi> The high Court of Parliament, even for this cauſe, ought ſomewhat to regard the Refractarie Miniſters.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="answer">
            <head>
               <hi>ANSWER.</hi> To the Conſequence.</head>
            <p n="1">1. NEither are the <hi>prayers</hi> of Schiſmatiques, much to be <hi>regarded</hi> neither will the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Court of Parliament altogether neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect the Refractarie Miniſters, but will labour by all good meanes, for their recalling: neither can the Refractarie Miniſters in Charitie, but ſtill pray for that high Court, yea in caſe they did not ſatiſfie their deſire.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If they had ſtill made conſcience of their dutie in their Miniſterie, their <hi>prayers</hi> had beene much more effectuall.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Errour is, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. And
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,</p>
         </div>
         <div n="13" type="argument">
            <head>XIII. ARGVMENT.</head>
            <p>SVurely (ſaith our Saviour) <hi>The harueſt is great, and the labourers are few, pray yee therefore the Lord of the harueſt, that he would thruſt forth labourers into his harveſt. Mat. 9.37.38.</hi> Will
<pb facs="tcp:21468:28"/>our <hi>Sauiour,</hi> haue all to pray the Lord of the harueſt, that he wold thrust forth labourers into his harueſt? and may any men then, by head and ſhoulders<note n="a" place="margin">They are not
<hi>thruſt out</hi> that run away. And they run away, that leaue their ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary calling for little or no cauſe at all.</note> thruſt labourers out of his harueſt? It would be accompted madneſſe, for a man to thruſt labourers out of his owne harueſt, when his harueſt is ready for the ſickle, and he hath not laborers enough. But it is impiety to thruſt labourers out of the Lord his harueſt, eſpecially ſuch as whom himſelfe had before thruſt forth into his harueſt, furniſhing them with ſickle and all other things neceſſary. And laſtly ſuch as had done good ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice in his harueſt. Againe, will our Sauiour, haue men onely to pray the Lord of the harueſt, for thru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting forth of labourers into his harueſt, and will hee haue them to do nothing elſe in this behalfe? As well may they thinke that they are onely to pray for their dayly bread, and that they neede to do nothing elſe for the getting thereof.</p>
            <div type="resolution">
               <head>Reſolution of the 13. Argument.</head>
               <p>Our Sauiour willeth all to pray the Lord of the Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt, that he would thruſt forth labourers into his harueſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ergo</hi> No man ought by head and ſhoulders to thruſt out labourers out of the harueſt.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="answer">
            <head>ANSWER.</head>
            <p n="1">1. I Grant the whole. If the ſuppliants will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance,
<hi>Why then do you ſilence &amp; depriue the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. I anſwer. They are not ſuch labourers, whom our Sauiour meaneth: neither are they <hi>thrust forth of the harueſt,</hi> for labouring, but for
<pb facs="tcp:21468:29"/>labouring as they ought not, for ſowing the tares of ſedition, ſchiſme and faction, for diſturbing the peace of the Church, and for moleſting other ſincere and faithfull labourers.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Errour is, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Alſo,
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="14" type="argument">
            <head>XIV. ARGRMENT.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Whoſoeuer</hi> (ſaith our Sauiour) <hi>ſhall be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of me and of my words, of them ſhall the ſonne of man be a ſhamed, when he ſhall come in his glory, and in the glory of the father, and of the holy Angels: Luc. 9.26.</hi> Is this to be vnderſtood onely of the time of perſecution, and not alſo, and much more, of the dayes of peace? Or are not they aſhamed of <hi>Chriſt</hi> and of his words, that will not ſpeake for him and<note n="a" place="margin">As if the diſciplinarian giddineſſe were <hi>Gods word.</hi>
               </note> his word? Nay let the contrary branch of the oppoſition touching the promiſe, made by our
<hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour</hi> for the confeſsing of them <hi>before his Father which is in heauen, that ſhall confeſſe him before men,</hi> ſuppreſſe this vaine imagination: Laſtly touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this point, will they not be aſhamed of Chriſt, but confeſſe him and his words before Tyrants in the time of fiery triall, that will not ſhew themſelues zealous for Chriſt and his words, before a<note n="b" place="margin">Here a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliants con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe that we profeſſe Chriſt and his word. Why do they exclaime the?</note> State fauouring, and profeſsing Chriſt and his words, in the dayes of peace? Truly God by his almighty power &amp; rich grace, may mightily<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Feare and weakneſſe</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooth, becauſe they will not part-take with Schiſmatikes.</note> ſtrengthen ſuch men in the dayes of trouble, (notwithſtanding their preſent feare and weakeneſſe) but certainely in reaſon this is little to
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:21468:29"/>be hoped for. Let no man therefore flatter or deceaue himſelfe with any ſuch poore, ſimple and ſhiftfull con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceite.</p>
            <div type="resolution">
               <head>Reſolution of the 14. Argument.</head>
               <p>Euery man ought freely to confeſse Christ before men in the time aſwell of tryall and perſecution, as of truce and peace.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ergo.</hi> The high Court of Parliament ought earneſtly to ſpeake for Chriſt and his word.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="answer">
            <head>ANSWER.</head>
            <p n="1">1. I Graunt the whole againe. What can this ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage the Refractarie Miniſters? It follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not, that therfore their Honours ſhold ſpeake for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For they are neither Chriſt, nor his word<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> neither is their quarell and contention, either for <hi>Christ,</hi> or for his <hi>Word,</hi> as hath beene declared before.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Errour is, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="15" type="argument">
            <head>XV. ARGVMENT.</head>
            <p>YOur zeale touching the Papiſts for more ſeuerity againſt them hereafter, that thereby they may be the more eaſily conuerted fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their damnable hereſies; is worthy euerlaſting renowne. But may it alſo pleaſe you to conſider, to what ende there ſhalbe more ſeuere lawes made, for the bringing of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to church, if there ſhal not likewiſe be<note n="a" place="margin">As who would ſay, there can be no ſufficient prouiſion of <hi>able Miniſters</hi> except Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticall Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters to make vp the nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber.</note> prouiſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that when they come there they may haue ſuch Miniſters as ſhalbe able ſubſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, &amp; ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly to confute their hereſies, &amp; to inſtruct
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:21468:30"/>them in the trueth and not ſuch, as against whom, in reſpect of their inſufficiency and weakenſſe, they ſhalbe able to take exception: yea whom alſo they ſhall deride: yea, and finally, by whom they ſhall be more confirmed in their hereſies: or at the leaſt, the more hardened againſt the trueth? Willany man<note n="b" place="margin">Why not?</note> ſay, there may be ſufficient miniſters enough, though all thoſe that are called refractary and vnconformable, be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled? I<note n="c" place="margin">Vaine <hi>hope.</hi> It ſhold ſeeme theſe ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ants are but little acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the Vniuerſities.</note> hope the wiſedome of the meaneſt of your Honourable aſſemblie is ſuch, that he wil heare this an hundred times, before he wil beceue it once: For ſith al that now are, and were before any proceeding againſt thoſe before mentioned, were not enough, ſufficiently to furniſh euery congregation, what will the paucity be, when from thoſe ſo many<note n="d" place="margin">An Hyper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bole, to make their num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber ſeeme the greater.</note> hundreds, as able as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other ſhalbe detracted.</p>
            <div type="resolution">
               <head>Reſolution of the 15 Argument.</head>
               <p>It is neceſſary that there be made prouiſion of ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent able Miniſters, one in euery congregation, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct the people in the truth, to confute the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ergo.</hi> The refractary Miniſters muſt needes be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="answer">
            <head>ANSWER.</head>
            <p n="1">1. AS if there were not <hi>able Miniſters</hi> enough, (God be praiſed) in both vniuerſities and other parts of this kingdome, (if competent maintenance could be procured for them) <hi>ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently</hi> to furniſh every Congregation, to inſtruct the people in religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to refute the Aduerſary, &amp;c. but that the ſmall handfull of Schiſmaticall Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters
<pb facs="tcp:21468:30"/>muſt needes be entreated to make vp the number.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Suppoſe there were not <hi>able miniſters</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, for this purpoſe: haue not the Refractary Miniſters then greater reaſon to iome with their Brethren, in preaching the Goſpell, confuting the Papiſts, &amp;c. then ſuperſtitiouſly to quarell about croſſe and ſurplice, and to ſorſake their neceſſary vocation and function?</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Error is, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="16" type="argument">
            <head>XVI. ARGVMENT.</head>
            <p>TOuching the matters of trouble, and moleſtation to the miniſters, hither to mentioned, viz.<note n="a" place="margin">Hence ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth what they be, that the Refracta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries are offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with. Why then do they pretend the <hi>Goſpel of Chriſt, the ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of the people, reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation with God &amp;c. Ad populu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> phaleras</hi>
               </note> Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription, Ceremonies, the ſtrict obſeruation of the booke, and other Conformity, all men know, what<note n="b" place="margin">And all by reaſon of the Refractary mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nare ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſion and contention there hath beene betwixt the miniſters of the word in this kingdome, and their bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, as in other Churches reformed, ſo eſpecially in the former part of his Maiesties Dominion in Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, and what hath beene written by one part (eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially by the<note n="c" place="margin">O,
<hi>Martin</hi> was a modeſt man.</note> conformable part)<note n="d" place="margin">They will offend, &amp; yet will not be told of it.</note> in diſgrace and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proch of the other. But eſpecially great hath bin the e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention and controuerſie heere at home: much more indeed for and about theſe things, then for or <hi>about any point of doctrine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is euident, not onely by moſt bitter<note n="e" place="margin">Heat of contention may carry men farther then were expedient. But are the Refractaries milder in this kind? Witneſſe all their pamphlets and Libels written againſt vs.</note> inuectiue ſermons priuate raylings, and publike diſgracefull bookes against them: (the moſt<note n="f" place="margin">A diſgracefull terme. But do they acknowledge themſelues
<hi>Non conformitanes</hi> and ſchiſmaticall?</note> Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>formitants<note n="g" place="margin">Suam ſcabiem aliis affricant.</note> thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
<pb facs="tcp:21468:31"/>that they never preach, ſpeake, or write a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing well, except in their preaching, talke and writing, they ſcourge thoſe whom they call Puritan, preſciſe, ſchiſmatical, and refractary miniſters) but alſo by the actuall ſeveritie againſt them. For it may be truely ſaid, that in<note n="h" place="margin">A malicious lye. There are few or none in the Church of England, ſo <hi>ignorant,</hi> &amp; ſo
<hi>ſcandalous</hi> in the Miniſtery as here the Suppliants in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinuate: &amp; if a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſuch be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs, ſure I am, that (vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on complaint or intimation otherwiſe) they are ſeuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cenſured &amp; puniſhed for it. Yet I muſt giue them to vnderſtand, that Scanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Miniſters for life, are more tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in the Church, then ſuch as be fac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious, ſchiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall, or ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous for do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine &amp; pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naticall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipts, <hi>Plus e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim nocent do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrinae ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la, quàm mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum delicta.</hi>
               </note> one yeare, and in one <hi>Dioces,</hi> more haue beene for theſe cauſes ſuſpended and deprived, then in full <hi>46.</hi> yeares throughout the whole Realme of <hi>England,</hi> either for vnſufficiencie, or for any matter of ſcandall: albeit it cannot bee denyed, that in ſome one <hi>Dioceſſe,</hi> there are more ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant &amp; ſcandolous miniſters worthy of deprivatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> there are<note n="j" place="margin">Animpud <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t and loud lie, without any ſhew of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bality.</note> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>formable miniſters in al <hi>Dioceſſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By this controverſie and contention among the miniſters, there hath beene no leſſe diſſention and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lienation of mindes and heartes, betwixt<note n="k" place="margin">The more haue the Schiſmaticall Miniſters to anſwer for, by whoſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fault all theſe ſtirres and broyles are rayſed in the Church.</note> other of his Maieſties ſubiects for the ſame things: yea, much ſeparation of many from their miniſters, as likewiſe betwixt themſelues. Now how dangerous this is for his Maieſtie &amp; for the whole Land, as it doth appeare by the<note n="l" place="margin">And all by reaſon of the pertinacy of the Refractary Miniſters.</note> encreaſe and courage of the common adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries the Papiſts, according as the miniſters and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple for thoſe cauſes haue bin moleſted &amp; diſgraced, ſo it is further evident by reaſon. Becauſe as the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord peace, and good agreement is a principall part of the ſtrength of a King &amp; kingdom ſo their diſcord &amp; contention, cannot but bee dangerous for King and kingdome. For our <hi>Saviour</hi> himſelfe (ſpeaking accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon ſpeech of other, ſaith, <hi>That a king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">Wherefore then do not they ioyne themſelues vnto the Church, and ceaſe to make a diuiſion amongſt vs?</note> 
               <hi>divided againſt it ſelfe, cannot ſtand. Mar.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:21468:31"/>
            <p>What is therefore to be done in this caſe? How may theſe contrverſies and contentions be wel pacified, &amp; beſt compounded Verily by imitating therin God him ſelfe, <hi>the God of peace.</hi> For as he is and muſt be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged beſt of alſo herein alſo, he hath given vs the beſt preſident, the beſt patterne. What is that?<note n="n" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. The time of the old Teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t being exſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, Chriſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boliſhed the Ceremoniall law, and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained the new Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment What will they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude from hence?</note> When he ſaw the great diviſion and hatred betwixt the Iewes and the Gentiles, <hi>he tooke away the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition wall betwixt them,</hi> which was alſo called by the name of <hi>hatred,</hi> becauſe for it the Iewes had ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Gentiles, and the Gentiles likewiſe the Iewes. What was the partition wal? <hi>The law of comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements ſtanding in ordinaunces,</hi> that is, in Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monyes, which hee himſelfe had given to the Iewes. <hi>Ephe. 2.14.15.</hi> For therby, cannot be vnderſtood the moral law, which from the beginning had as wel con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned the Gentiles, as the Iewes: But the Ceremoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all law being that, in reſpect wherof, the Iewes in pride had co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned the Gentils, &amp; for which the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tils likewiſe, in no leſſe malice had envied the Iewes, as hauing ſuch a law by themſelues as for the which, they neither would nor might communicate with the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tils in their heatheniſh worſhip: the Lord therefore did altogether remoue the ſame, that ſo not only they <hi>which were once far from God, might bee made neere by the bloud of Chriſt</hi> (whereby the partiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on wall was broken downe) but that <hi>they alſo that had bin before twaine, might be made one</hi> (as it were two houſes made one, by breaking downe of one wall, or two fieldes layd into one by taking away of one hedge) <hi>that ſo there might be peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Lord might haue communicated the Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of the Iewes vnto the Ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tils, or given new vnto
<pb facs="tcp:21468:32"/>both. But ſith he made this peace onely by removing thoſe Ceremonies altogether, that himſelfe had once inſtituted, and did<note n="o)" place="margin">What? <hi>Not any?</hi> No Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments? nor other ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies?</note> not ordaine any in their place, then conſider (I beſeech you) in your godly wiſdomes, how much more it behooueth all thoſe Ceremonies &amp; ordinances, which we e onely in vented by man, to be<note n="p)" place="margin">They wold bring Cyclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picall ataxie into the church.</note> vtterly removed, having eſpecially<note n="q)" place="margin">Falſe. They are as it were the bondes of ſocietie, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides other vſes for edification</note> no neceſſarie vſe, but being rather bones of contention betwixt bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, and children of the ſame Father &amp; Mother, and coheyres of the ſame inheritance: as alſo people of the ſame Nation, and ſubiects of the ſame King and So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraigne. Yea, conſider (I beſeech you againe) the more ſeriouſly, how neceſſary it will be, thus to make<note n="r)" place="margin">If the Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliants requeſt were granted in the Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, yet would the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fractary Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters be reſtles ſtill, vntil they had altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther brought in their New Diſcipline: &amp; (peradue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture) more reſtles then alſo then euer they were before.</note> peace, not onely becauſe this peace will be exceedingly bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiall (as hath beene ſhewed) to King and kingdome, eſpecially the common aduerſaries ſo now combining themſelues againſt vs) but alſo becauſe it will be a worke moſt acceptable to God. For <hi>Bleſſed are the</hi>
               <note n="s" place="margin">Sound and ſolide <hi>Peace</hi> will neuer be wrought, but by recalling the Refractary Miniſters fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Schiſme and faction vnto perfect obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience.</note> 
               <hi>peace makers for they ſhall be called the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God.</hi> Math. <hi>5.9.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="resolution">
               <head>Reſolution of the 16. Argument.</head>
               <p>The matters in queſtion, <hi>viz.</hi> Subſcriptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Ceremonies, the ſtrict Obſeruation of the Booke, and other Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie, are not of any neceſſarie vſe, but are cauſes of diuiſion, and bones of contention amongst vs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ergo.</hi> They both conveniently may, and ought to be taken away.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="answer">
            <head>ANSWER.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>I.</hi> To the Antecedent.</head>
               <p n="1">1. IF the matters in queſtion betweene vs, be
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:21468:32"/>but <hi>Subſcription, Ceremonies, &amp;c.</hi> as here the Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliants ingenuouſly confeſſe, wherfore then haue they hitherto mainely cried out, that their conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was about the
<hi>Cauſe of God</hi> &amp; his <hi>Word, whole Chriſt</hi> and his
<hi>Goſpell,</hi> the <hi>Miniſtery</hi> thereof and <hi>Saluation</hi> of the people?</p>
               <p n="2">2. Albeit we alſo do not hold <hi>Subſcription, Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies &amp;c.</hi> to be abſolutely neceſſary to ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, nor to be impoſed vpon euery Church (for why ſhould not other Churches vſe their owne liberty?) yea and our Church hath power to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter theſe particulars: yet we know, that ſome Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances and Ceremonies, are euen neceſſary for the gathering of aſſemblies, eſtabliſhing of a Church, and be as it were the bonds and linkes of ſociety.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Yea euen theſe particulars, <hi>Subſcription, Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies &amp;c.</hi> being impoſed by the Church, and commanded by the Magiſtrate, are neceſſary to be obſerued vnder payne of ſinne, ſeeing <hi>he that reſiſteth auctority, reſiſteth the ordinance of God. Rom.</hi> 13.</p>
               <p n="4">4. And that they are things indifferent in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, and may be vſed without ſinne, wee haue proued at large, in a peculiar booke writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of that Argument. <hi>Lib. de Adiaphoris.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. Now that they are become the <hi>bones of conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> &amp; <hi>cauſes of diuiſion</hi> among vs, is very much to be lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted, ſeeing the free courſe of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell is ſomewhat troubled, and the common Eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie adua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taged therby. But the faulte teſts on the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, who of meere ſuperſtition and groſſe ignorance,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:21468:33"/>cannot finde in their conſciences to embrace the holſome Ordinances and Conſtitutions of the Church, not any way preiudiciall vnto the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, nor repugnant vnto the word of God, but moſt agreeable and conſonant vnto the ſame.</p>
               <p n="16">16. The Errour is, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. And <hi>Crimen falſi</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>II. To the Conſequence.</head>
               <p n="1">1. The Antecedent being declared to be falſe, the Conſequence cannot be true.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Errour is, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="17" type="argument">
            <head>XVII. ARGVMENT.</head>
            <p>IN the next place (that I may heape vp many things together, and contriue many arguments into one) I do offer to your wiſe &amp; godly conſiderations, the works of God amongst vs: his workes of Iuſtice, &amp; his works of mercy: together with the<note n="a)" place="margin">They miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take the <hi>Ends:</hi> as thoſe Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles did, who offirmed, they were plagued, becauſe of the Chriſtians contempt of their Gods.</note> ends for the which he hath wrought them before vs and the vſes, which he would haue vs to make of them. First therefore be yee pleaſed to call to minde, the late mightie and fearefull peſtilence wherby in all places (almoſt) of the land, but chiefly here in London, the Lord <hi>made heapes vpon heapes.</hi> Doth the Lord chaſtiſe particular perſons, <hi>that he may teach them in his lawe, Pſal. 94, 12.</hi> drawe them neerer vnto him, <hi>and make them</hi> more plentifully <hi>partakers of his holineſſe?</hi> Heb. <hi>12.10.</hi> Yea, &amp; <hi>that they may be more zealous &amp; amend.</hi> Reuel. <hi>3.19.</hi> And are not theſe as well the ends, why he chaſtiſeth whole States, Churches and kingdomes, as the<note n="b)" place="margin">It is true: the Lord cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recteth vs for our ſinnes, &amp; the Refractary Miniſters, ſchiſme is no meane cauſe of our puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> ſinnes of whole States, Churches and kingdoms are the cauſes that firſt moue him ſo to chaſtiſe them?
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:21468:33"/>Yea, is not this the more to be conſidered, becauſe this rod of God doth ſtill remaine and linger, as here in
<hi>Londo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> ſo alſo in divers other places of the land? for doth not the Lord hereby intimate vnto vs, that yet that is not performed by vs, which he looked for fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs?</p>
            <p>Againe, is it altogether to be neglected, that he hath ſo mittigated this his ſeverity toward vs as he hath? And that he hath in part commanded his Angell to put vp his ſword, and not to ſmite ſo many as before he had done? And doth not the Lord by ſmiting vs in ſuch ſort, threaten, that if for all this we ſhew no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter fruites of amendment,
<hi>he will plague vs yet ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven times worſe?</hi> Levit. <hi>26.18.</hi> By healing vs alſo in part, doth he not admoniſh vs, that if we do not yet repent, but continue <hi>ſtill to ſinne againſt him, a worſe thing ſhall come vnto vs?</hi> Ioh. <hi>5.14.</hi> O<note n="c)" place="margin">This Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrophe ſhold haue bin more fitly applyed vnto the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fractary Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters,</note> yee that doe now repreſent the body of this land, conſider of this matter.</p>
            <p>What ſhall I heere ſpeake of our late great danger by the late moſt bloudie, horrible, vnnaturall and mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous conſpiracie of the Papiſts; as againſt all in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall ſo ſpecially againſt you that are now eſſembled, in this high Court of Parliament? Would the Lord haue every perſon to prouoke his <hi>owne ſoule to praiſe the Lord, for redeeming his ſoule from the graue,</hi> Pſa. <hi>103.4.</hi> And would he not have the whole land &amp; ſpecially you that are now aſsebled in high court of Parliament, repreſenting the whole land and in ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall maner delivered, to enter into ſerious conſultatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; deliberatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with your ſelues, <hi>what to render vnto the Lord, for al his benefits towards you,</hi> Pſ. <hi>116.12</hi> Though<note n="d)" place="margin">I will not deſcant on the Suppliants meaning in alleadging this example. The wiſe may conſider it.</note> Hezekiah hauing recouered health, we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t firſt
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:21468:34"/>into the houſe of God, and made there a Pſalme of thankeſgiuing for his recovery, which yet remaineth in holy writ, as an everlaſting monument of his thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe; yet becauſe in other things, he was not gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally ſo circumſpect and carefull, of all obedience to God as he ſhould haue beene, <hi>but his heart was lift vp within him,</hi> it is ſaid that <hi>he rendred not vnto the Lord, according vnto the reward beſtowed vpon him;</hi> and that therefore <hi>wrath came from the Lord againſt him, againſt Ieruſalem, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Iuda. 2.</hi> Chro.
<hi>32.25.</hi> So let this be conſidered, that yee may provoke your ſelues to the more publike teſtimonie of thankfulneſſe, for our late publike deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerance. And becauſe <hi>mercy</hi> (even towards the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of men)
<hi>is more deſired then ſacrifice,</hi> and that therefore mercy towards their ſoules, is much more acceptable vnto God, for which cauſe it is there ſaid, that <hi>the Lord doth</hi> alſo <hi>more deſire the knowledge of God, then burnt offrings.</hi> Hoſ. <hi>6.6.</hi> Therefore alſo, as God his goodneſſe towards the whole land is knowne to all the world, ſo let all the world know, and let all ages to come bee witneſſes, of our thankfulneſſe for the ſame, by your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent mercy towards the<note n="e)" place="margin">To wit, by ſetling the ſtate thereof, and prouiding ſeuere lawes againſt here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall Papiſts, and ſchiſmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Refracta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries.</note> Church. He that biddeth vs <hi>to call vpon him in the day of our trouble,</hi> and promiſeth to <hi>deliuer vs,</hi> requireth alſo <hi>that wee ſhould glorifie him.</hi> Pſal. <hi>50 15.</hi> How much more then ought we to glorifie him, being in the day of our trouble delivered before we called vpon him?</p>
            <p>Verily (most Honorable aſſembly) in this reſpect our deliueracce is the greater, then the deliverance either of the Iewes from the bloudy intent of <hi>Haman,</hi>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:21468:34"/>or of our ſelues in the yeare. <hi>1588.</hi> For the Lord did not worke thoſe deliverances without the meanes of prayer and faſting: but this, his owne right hand hath brought to paſſe, before that ever wee did open our lipps vnto him in that behalfe. Yea, herein is our deliuerance alſo the greater, becauſe, though the miſchiefe plotted againſt vs was but bodily, yet the miſchiefe plotted againſt ours and all poſterity was ſpirituall, even to haue reduced them to the former bondage of popiſh blindneſſe, ſuperſtition and Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, ſo to haue periſhed everlaſtingly: and therefore wee that ſhould haue beene conſumed touching our bodies, and outward ſtates, in this intended maſſacre, (if it had proceeded) ſhould haue beene much better, then they that ſhould haue liued. As it belongeth ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to all, at all times to glorifie God for this great deliverance, ſo ſpecially it belongeth to you that are now aſſembled in this high Court of Parliament</p>
            <p>The Lord eareth not for any obſervation of a day onely, in remembrance of his me eies, nor for bare words in commendation and celebration of his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, except that otherwiſe we doe <hi>diſpoſe our way aright:</hi> For this is the beſt <hi>prayſe whereby hee is glorified. Pſal. 50.25.</hi> Yea even nowe, and at this Seſſion, doth the Lord require this of you. For hath not his hand of ſickneſſe in many places continued, and doth it not ſtill hoover o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er vs from before the firſt ſummoning of this Parliament, to this preſent Seſſion? And did not God reveale his mercy in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealing the late treaſon, and delivering vs from it, immediatly before the laſt Seſſion, that your meeting might be proroged, whereby in the time of Interim,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:21468:35"/>ye might haue the more leaſure, the better to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berate and conſult, what at this your aſſembly might moſt make for the glory of his name, and the good of his Church? And will ye now diſſolue your metting without doing of further matter in<note n="f)" place="margin">As if no good could be done vnto the Church, but the Reſtitutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Scuma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, which indeed is no good.</note> that behalfe then yet ye haue done?</p>
            <p>Againe, are not many of you auncient, and in that reſpect never againe like to be of any other Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? which alſo of the youngeſt and luſtieſt of you knoweth, either that he ſhall liue to an other Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or to another Seſſion of this Parliament: Or if he ſhall liue to another Parliament, that he ſhalbe choſen to bee againe thereof? Or livyng to another Seſsion of this Parliament, that he ſhall haue health and ſtrength to be preſent thereat? Are not ſome wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy men, that were at the former Seſſions of this Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, now at reſt with the Lord? Yea, are not ſome other that were living and in health at the time of the laſt Seſſion, now alſo (before the beginyng of this Seſsion) gathered to their Fathers?</p>
            <p>Yea further, becauſe divers of the miniſters de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived and ſilenced (being partly very aged, and partly conſumed with<note n="g)" place="margin">What god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe is there in wilfull and malicious co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fronting the Magiſtrate, in repining at their brethren and ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous forſaking their calling, liuings, flocke and all, to the vndoing of themſelues, their wiues, children and friends?</note> Godly griefe,) not ſo much for their owne troubles, as for the deſolation of the Churches, both preſently ſeene, and for future times by the preſent to be prognoſticated, in as much as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny moſt<note n="h)" place="margin">A c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lumni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus Cenſure.</note> vnworthy perſons are thruſt into their places, (in which conſideration, as <hi>Eliſha</hi> wept, by the ſpirit of prophecie, to foreſee the miſerable havocke that <hi>Hazael</hi> ſhould make of the people of
<hi>Iſrael</hi> tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching their bodies, <hi>2 Kings 8.11.12.</hi> So what Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an heart can refraine weeping and bleeding, to fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinke
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:21468:35"/>of the ſpiritual ſpoyle, that will be made in the Church by<note n="b)" place="margin">A manifeſt ſlander. But if it be ſo, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore do not the Refractary Miniſters re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ine their pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to keepe out ſuch?</note> blind guides, corrupt teachers, &amp; careles: yea wicked and vngodly Paſtors: becauſe (I ſay) many faithfull miniſters deprived and ſilenced, partly by age, and partly by Godly griefe, are ſo neere the finiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of their race, that the ground for their graue is in a manner already meaſured: therfore ye that are the Lords worthies, now aſſembled in this High and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable Court, do that, that is to bee done by you, for the glory of God, and comfort of his Churches and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, with the more ſpeed and expedition, that ſuch ſeruants of God as are ſo neere their end, may yet be ſomewhat reviued and comforted before their end, bleſſe you and yours before they die, and ſo take their leaues alſo of you and yours, with the more peace and ioye to their owne ſoules.</p>
            <p>As your houſe of Parliament at the laſt Seſſion therof, ſhould paſſiuely haue beene the houſe of blood, yea the fountaine (in ſome ſorte) of blood, that even from thence ſhould haue flowed ſtreames and rivers of blood through out the whole land: ſo let it at this Seſſion bee actiuely the houſe of comfort yea a foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of comfort, that from thence may flowe a ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver (as it were the river of God) and a floude of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual comfort, icy and gladneſſe to al the land. To all the land<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Yea to all Nations that know the Lord and cal vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his name: yea to al poſterity. As the firſt day of the laſt Seſſion, ſhould haue bin, <hi>a day of darknes &amp; of blacknes, a day of clouds &amp; of obſcurity</hi> (as <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el</hi> ſpeaketh ch. <hi>2.2.</hi>) ſo let the laſt day of this Seſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be a bright and cleare ſunſhine day, a day of light, a day of
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:21468:36"/>comfort and refreſhing from the Lord. As the Lords enimyes, the bloody and mercileſſe Papiſts (merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe to them ſelues, in murdering themſelues here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore and of late, and therefore much more merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe vnto other) As theſe men would haue made themſelues as a fire to devoure all before <hi>them, and as a flame to burne vp all behind them. Ioel. 2.3.</hi> So be ye that are the Children of God, <hi>and ſhould therefore be mercifull, as your Father alſo is mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful, Luk. 6.6.</hi> Be ye (I ſay) as it were the <hi>rayne: even as the firſt and the latter raine,</hi> (Ioel. <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.24</hi>) <hi>as their wrath ſhold haue bin like the roaring of a Lyon</hi> (as <hi>Salomon</hi> ſpeaketh of <hi>the wrath of a King</hi>) ſo let your favour be (as <hi>Samon</hi> ſpeaketh of <hi>the favour of a King</hi>) <hi>like the dewe vpon the graſſe. Pro. 1.12.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By this mercy that hitherto I haue (as it were at the barre of your Iuſtice) pleaded for, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked you vnto, yee ſhall not onely treaſure vp<note n="a)" place="margin">The Suppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ants ſpeak by contraries.</note> comfort to your ſelues againſt the day of your death, when ye ſhall moſt stand in neede of comfort, but yee ſhall alſo make your old age the more honorable: yea after your dayes here ended, your name and memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry will be honorable with all poſteritie. Whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>efore did <hi>Deborah</hi> ſay, <hi>that Iael the wife of Heber ſhould be bleſſed aboue other women, yea bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed aboue other women dwelling in tents?</hi> Iudg. <hi>5.24.</hi> Becauſe
<hi>with an hammer ſhee had driven a nayle</hi> ſo deepe into the head of
<hi>Siſera</hi> ſleeping in her tent, that he did never awake.</p>
            <p>If ſuch a ſentence of bleſſedneſſe were prophecied of
<hi>Iael,</hi> for making away onely an outward enimy of
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:21468:36"/>the outward ſtate of the Church, howe much more ſhall ye be bleſſed: yea bleſſed aboue many former Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament men, if as ſome haue made a beginning of the deſolation of the whore of Rome in theſe landes ſo ye ſhall make perfect that beginning, and vtterly take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way whatſoever of her<note n="l)" place="margin">We muſt wiſely diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh between ſuch things as are proper vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Papacie and what they haue by vſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation, but are proper vnto the true Church of God.</note> ornaments yet remayning, wherwith ſhe and her Prieſts were wont to be decked, and are yet decked, and wherwith alſo her Idols were wont to be worſhipped, and are yet worſhipped? And if as other haue already (in ſome ſort) begunne to driue the naile into the head of the Archenimy (next vnder Sathan himſelfe) of the ſpirituall ſtate of the Church, ſo ye ſhall alſo driue the ſame further? Yea if like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe as the Papiſts comforted themſelues touching their contrived and hoped for deſtruction of our per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and of our religion, ſaying (in dreaming ſort) a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong themſelues, as <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaid to the Iſraelits, <hi>theſe men and this religion which yee haue hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto ſeene, ye ſhall never ſee againe:</hi> ſo likwiſe ye by the ſword of the word of the Lord, and of your au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, (as it were) <hi>by the ſword of the Lord and of Gideon,</hi> Iudg. <hi>7.20.</hi> if (I ſay) ye ſhal ſo cut of the tayle of the ſaid whore of Rome, and (as it were) <hi>her branch and ruſh,</hi> that there ſhalbe no more hope left to her lovers here amongeſt vs, of ever committing the like ſpirituall fornication with her hereafter, that heretofore they haue done: that ſo we may comfortab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly apply the former words of <hi>Moſes</hi> to our ſelues and to our children, touching the Romiſh religion and all the<note n="m)" place="margin">Proper therevnto.</note> appurtainance thereof, which wee haue ſeene, <hi>that we ſhall never ſee them againe, Exod. 14.23.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yea, let the late conſpiracie of Papiſts before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:21468:37"/>prouoke you ſo much the more carefully, and firmly, to aboliſh their whole religion, to the leaſt hem of every garment and Ceremony thereof, as alſo the more ſurely to eſtabliſh the Goſpell with all things ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaining therevnto, and every holy meanes for the beſt ſupporting thereof, by how much more, the curſed fruites thereof haue proclaimed it, and daily do pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime it, to be odious and abhominable in the ſight of God. Laſtly, though they were then diſappointed, yet your wiſdome is ſuch, that I hope yee need not be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhed, either not to thinke that they will hereafter be idle and giue over their occupation, of wicked and treaſonable imaginations, or not to neglect, by all good meanes poſsible, to prevent whatſoever future trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherie and conſpiracie, yet they ſhall in their darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, further practiſe againſt vs.</p>
            <div type="resolution">
               <head>Reſolution of the 17. Argument.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>In this Argument the Suppliants,</hi> heaping <hi>(as themſelues profeſſe)</hi> many things together, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triving many Arguments into one, <hi>do certainly ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie worthily and Chriſtianly diſcourſe, as of ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie other things, ſo eſpecially concerning the Lords great mercies, in the miraculous delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, as of your Honourable Houſe of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſo alſo conſequently of the whole State and Kingdome, thereby redeeming both our Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies from corporall, and our Soules from Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all intended captiuitie of that bloodie</hi> Man of Sinne, the childe of Perdition. <hi>Which verily ſhould prouoke every good Chriſtian to ſpeciall thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:21468:37"/>vnto our heauenly Father, to repentance for our former tranſgreſſions, to preſent dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence in our ſeverall vocations, and ever here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after to keepe a more vigilant and watchfull eye over the perfidious and treacherous Aduerſarie. But let vs examine how the Suppliants applie theſe things to their purpoſe.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="answer">
            <div n="1" type="reason">
               <head>I. REASON.</head>
               <p>God ſent lately amongst vs a mightie and fearefull peſtilence, for omiſsion of ſome dutie which ſhould haue beene performed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ergo.</hi> The high Court of Parliament is preſently to reſtore the refractarie Miniſters, eſpecially ſeeing the plague doth ſtill hover over our heads.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>ANSWER.</head>
               <p n="1">1. TO let the Antecedent paſſe, which yet is not ſo fully and warily laide downe, as it ought to haue beene. Who doth not ſee the weakneſſe of the Conſequence. For doth GOD plague vs becauſe <hi>of the proceedings against the Refractarie Miniſters;</hi> and not rather for our horrible ſinnes of ſecuritie, pride, vnthankeful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe &amp;c. This is certaine: and that reſts to be proued ſtill.</p>
               <p>The Errour is manifold. 1. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.2.
<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.3. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.4. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="reason">
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:21468:38"/>
               <head>II. REASON.</head>
               <p>God hath lately delivered the Houſe of Parliament &amp; the whole land from a bloudie intended maſſacre.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ergo.</hi> That honourable Court ſpecially ought to teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie their thankfulneſſe vnto God, by reſtoring the Refractarie Miniſters.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>ANSWER.</head>
               <p n="1">1. AS if there were no other meanes whereby that
<hi>honourable Court</hi> might <hi>teſtifie their thankfulneſſe,</hi> but by reſtoring Schiſmaticall Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtours vnto the Church, the more to diſturbe the peace thereof.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The errour is, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Alſo,
<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="reason">
               <head>III. REASON.</head>
               <p>Many of the honourable Lords, and other members of the Parliament, are very ancient and ſtriken in yeares; and therefore never againe like to be of any other Parliament.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ergo.</hi> They ought to do good now, by reſtoring the Deprived and Silenced Miniſters.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>ANSWER.</head>
               <p n="1">1. BVt it hath not beene yet proued, that to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore the Refractarie Miniſters, is <hi>to doe Good,</hi> and not rather to doe hurt; and to ſinne by being cauſe of nouriſhing faction and diſſention in the Church.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Errours be, 1. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 2.
<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 3. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="reason">
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:21468:38"/>
               <head>IV. REASON.</head>
               <p>The Refractarie Miniſters would be very glad, if they were comforted, reſtored, and let alone.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ergo.</hi> They ought ſo to be.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>ANSWER.</head>
               <p>SO would all Schiſmatiques, Heretiques, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, Atheiſts, yea all malefactors, murtherers, theeues, cut purſes, <hi>be very glad, if they were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted,</hi> deliuered, <hi>and let alone.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="reason">
               <head>V. REASON.</head>
               <p>The Houſe of Parliament, by their mercy ſhewed to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Refractarie Miniſters, ſhall not onely treaſure vp comfort vnto themſelues againſt the day of their death, but ſhall alſo make their olde Age the more honourable, and their names memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable amongst all poſteritie.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ergo.</hi> They ought ſo to do.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>ANSWER.</head>
               <p n="1">1. IF by <hi>Mercy,</hi> they meane their reclaiming from Schiſme and faction, I grant the whole.</p>
               <p n="2">2. But if they meane their <hi>Reſtoring</hi> againe, they continuing ſtill the ſame men they are now: then is the Antecedent a foule begging of the Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and the Argument inconſequent.</p>
               <p n="3">3. For, contrariwiſe it may be concluded. <hi>The Houſe of Parliament, by reſtoring Schiſmaticall Miniſters, to diſquiet the peace of the Church; ſhall not onely attract guilt and remorſe of conſcience; but alſo preiudice their honourable Age, and make their names reproachfull amongst all poſteritie.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="reason">
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:21468:39"/>
               <head>VI. REASON.</head>
               <p>As Iael was bleſſed aboue other women dwelling in tents, for driving a nayle into Siſeraes head: So ſhould theſe Parliament Men, be bleſsed aboue ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny former if they vtterly tooke away all the Whore of Romes ornaments yet remayning &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ergo.</hi> They ought to do ſo.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>ANSWER.</head>
               <p n="1">1. THe inſtance is altogither different. For
<hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſera</hi> was a ſpeciall enemie of the Children of Iſrael, and of the Church of God, (<hi>Iudg.</hi> 4.2.) But the <hi>Ornaments</hi> the Suppliants ſpeake of, are the good Creatures of God, hauing no hurt or ill in them.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Neither were the Popiſh idolatrous Prieſtes ever
<hi>decked with our Ornaments,</hi> neither are they now.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Neither were <hi>our Ornaments</hi> ever
<hi>worſhipped or abuſed to Idolatrie,</hi> neither are they yet.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Neither if they had beene, is it abſolutely ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie to deſtroy the Subſtance of them, togi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the abuſe: but the abuſe is to be aboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, and the true vſe reſtored. The reaſons here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and cautions to be vſed in this point, I haue layde downe in another place. <hi>Chap.</hi> 11. <hi>Lib. de Adiaph.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. The Errour is, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. And,
<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="18" type="argument">
            <head>XVII. ARGVMENT.</head>
            <p>TO conclude therefore, whilſt ye haue time, and whileſt it is called to day, feare that ye ſhal never
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:21468:39"/>hereafter haue the like time and oportunitie that now ye haue: and therefore as <hi>Bathſheba</hi> ſaid to her moſt princely ſonne <hi>Lemuell, Open thy mouth for the dumme, and in the cauſe of all the children of deſtruction, open thy mouth: iudge righteouſly, and iudge the afflicted and the poore. Pro. 31.8.9.</hi> So ſay I, to all them that by their place may any way do good to the Church of God, and to any afflicted and poore members thereof. Yea, as the ſaid <hi>Queene Bathſheba</hi> ſaith before, <hi>giue yee ſtrong drinke, to him that is ready to periſh, and wine vnto them that haue griefe of heart, that he may drinke, and forget his povertie, and remember his miſerie no more, Pro.
31.6.7.</hi> So I doe wiſh all them that are of any authoritie, or in any place of grace and favour, eſpecially this preſent high Court of Parliament, to giue a plentiful boll of the ſtrong drinke of their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable favour, yea an whole flagon ful of the wine of their grace, that they that are now poore, and haue bin long heavy harted for the<note n="a)" place="margin">Beging of the Queſtion. Let the ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ants looke in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to themſelues and bevvaile the <hi>corruptions</hi> they ſhall ſee there.</note> corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s &amp; ruins of <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> &amp; that in the greif of their hearts are ready to pe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>riſh, may drink ſo deeply therof, <hi>that they may forget their poverty, and reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber their miſery no more.</hi> Iob ſaid, that <hi>he had not conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned the iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of his ſerva<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, neither of his maide, when they conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with him.</hi> Iob. <hi>31.13.</hi> How much leſſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is the<note n="b)" place="margin">Impudent begging the Queſtion.</note> iudgment of the miniſters of the goſpel, yea, of the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther 06 of vs al (the Church of God) yea, of God himſelf, of Chriſt Ieſus, of the holy Angels, of our ſelues &amp; our poſterity, &amp; finally of king and kingdom (as hath bin ſhewed) to be neglected? As
<hi>Hama<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> ſaid of the Iewes <hi>to Ahaſhueroſh, that they were a people ſcattered &amp;
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:21468:40"/>diſperſed among the people in al provinces of his kingdome, having lawes divers from all people, and not obſerving the Kings lawes, and that ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it was not for the Kings profite to ſuffer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> Eſter. <hi>3.8.</hi> So I am not ignorant that theſe miniſters of the Goſpell. of whom I haue now in theſe Arguments made ſo often mention, are<note n="c" place="margin">And that iuſtly, if you meane <hi>the ſtate of the Church.</hi>
               </note> charged as enimies to the ſtate, perturbers of the Church, ſeditious, ſchiſmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call &amp;c.</p>
            <p>But if it were lawfull and free for theſe men to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postulate with the ſtate touching the former matters, as <hi>David</hi> did with the Lords annoynted <hi>Saule,</hi> they might not onely ſay with <hi>David Wherefore do ye giue eare to mens words, that ſay, behold</hi> David
<hi>ſeeketh evill againſt you? 1. Sam. 24.10.</hi> But they might alſo plead their innocency, as <hi>David</hi> doth his, verſe. <hi>12. Vnderſtand and ſee, that there is neither evil, nor wickedneſſe in vs, neither haue wee ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned againſt you.</hi> But in the meane time, this they may boldly ſay, that as the former hath bin an old ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſation in all ages, even againſt the beſt friends of the Church and ſtate, ſo it is anſwered by the <hi>D. King</hi> in his <hi>42.</hi> lecture vpon
<hi>Ionas,</hi> pag. <hi>171.</hi> out of <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> that ſuch accuſations are rather by <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiction then by conviction.</hi> And therefore as our moſt gratious <hi>Queene</hi> of moſt happie memory
<hi>Queene Elizabeth,</hi> before ſhe was <hi>Queene,</hi> in her distreſſe, in the dayes of <hi>Queene Mary,</hi> wrot with her Diamond in a glaſſe window at Woodſtocke.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Much ſuſpected by me,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nothing proved can be.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>Even<note n="d" place="margin">Not <hi>ſo.</hi>
               </note> ſo may theſe men both ſpeake and write, the
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:21468:40"/>ſame of themſelues.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>As for ſuch<note n="e" place="margin">An vniuſt calumnie.</note> accuſers as are alwayes provoking all men, eſpecially Princes, and Nobles againſt them, I wiſh them to take heed of that fearefull curſſe, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">As if
<hi>Dauids</hi> caſe and the Schiſmaticall Miniſters were the ſame.</note> 
               <hi>David curſed thoſe children of men before the Lord, that had ſturred vp</hi> Saule <hi>againſt him, and that by that meanes had caſt him out from abiding in the inheritance of the Lord, ſaying go ſerue other Gods, 1</hi> Sam <hi>26.19.</hi> For my part, I pray that God may giue them a better minde, that ſo they may rather be the bleſſed of the Lord.</p>
            <p>Touching other alſo that haue beene, or are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, in<note n="g" place="margin">In obeying the Superiot Magiſtrate, &amp; executing Iuſtice.</note> ſilencing, depriving, or otherwiſe moleſting of miniſters, for omiſſion of Ceremonies, not obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the booke of Common prayer in that ſtrict man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner that they doe vrge the ſame, and for other con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formitie, (though in other things they doe and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but iuſtifie them) I am ſo farre from wiſhing the leaſt evill vnto them, that I doe heartely praye the Lord (who hath the hearts of all in his handes) to worke ſuch a gratious change in them, that they may by all meanes as much further the worke of God, as by their former dealing they haue<note n="h" place="margin">Falſe.</note> hindred the ſame. That ſo they may haue all true honor in this life, and bee eternally bleſſed in the life to come. Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally concerning our moſt gracious Soveraigne, I haue prayed, I doe pray, and whileſt I liue I will pray for him, as <hi>Salomon</hi> prayed for himſelfe, <hi>1.</hi> Kings <hi>2.45. Let King Iames be bleſſed, and let his throne bee ſtabliſhed before the Lord for ever:</hi> yea, ſo I pray the Lord to bleſse him, with our Noble <hi>Queene,</hi> and all their Royall iſſue, that their earthly
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:21468:41"/>kingdome being ended, they may haue the heavenly, and there raigne with Chriſt Ieſus the King of Kings for ever, and ever. To this prayer, <hi>Let all the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſay,</hi> Amen.</p>
            <div type="resolution">
               <head>Reſolution of the 18. Argument.</head>
               <p>The high Court of Parliament is bound ſpeedily to open their mouth for the dumbe, to iudge righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, to iudge the afflicted and the poore, to give ſtrong wine to him that is ready to periſh; and not to contemne the iudgement of the meanest Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ergo.</hi> They are bound, ſpeedily to reſtore the Refracta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie Miniſters.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="answer">
            <head>ANSWER.</head>
            <p n="1">1. THis Argument is parallel, &amp; the very ſame with the
8. Argument before, and is there anſwered.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In one word. I grant the Antecedent, and deny the Conſequence; becauſe the Refractarie Miniſters are not ſuch, as be ſpecified in the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecedent, as is often declared before.</p>
            <p n="3">3, The Errour is, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.Alſo,
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="conclusion">
            <pb n="79" facs="tcp:21468:41"/>
            <head>The Concluſion.</head>
            <p>HItherto (Right Reuerend and Honourable) according vnto my weake abilitie, I haue with as much breuity as I could (ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wordes ought to be numbred vnto ſo great States) defended the equity of the proceedings againſt the clamors of theſe phanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtique Plaintiſes. Wherein, as I cannot but very much lament this their contentious and wrangling humour. So alſo (albeit in the ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clipſe of their charity, they eſteeme of vs, that ſtand in the breach, as of the greateſt enemyes they haue) I cannot in like manner, but grieue in my very ſoule, when I heare them complaine of their Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerty and want of the benefits of this life, as they do in ſundry pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of this Supplication: which would God their ſingularity hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred them not to enioy, as well as we. For (alas!) what pleaſure can we take to ſee them depriued thereof? We al beleeue in one Chriſt according vnto the truth of his Goſpell, we do, or ſhould obey one King, our peace is their peace, and our liberty theirs, if they will be content (as they ought) to inioy it: We can afford them roome a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs, we enuie them no preferments and places of any good and honourable ſeruice in the Church, according to their worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and ability to deale therein. And whereas they lay the blame vpon vs, who are their Brethren, to be <hi>alwayes at the Nobles and Princes elbowes</hi> to ſtirre them vp, and <hi>to provoke al men againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:</hi> let them looke into themſelues, and acknowledge their owne er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, and we aſſure our ſelues, vpon the compaſſionate clemencie &amp; mercifull nature of our ſoueraigne Lord, that they ſhalbe graciouſly and louingly embraced, and that they ſhall want no manner of thing that is fit for them. Let them be aſhamed of their feeding of ſhales and huskes at other mens trenchers, as they do, without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, either vnto the neceſſity of their eſtate, or to the dignity of their calling: whereas the ſincere Miniſters of the Goſpell (as a lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Man well obſerueth) ought to be maintayned, not by popular contributions, but by ſet ſtipends or tithes, &amp; that for many reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s.<note place="margin">Aret. in Probl. loc. 142. pag. 426.</note> 1. <hi>That the occaſion of marchandizing the word of God might bee auoyded. For otherwiſe, crafty, vnfaithful and hypocritical Miniſters would apply themſelues to their affections, whom they ſuppoſed would giue them moſt.</hi> 2. <hi>That Euangelicall liberty of reprehenſion might ſtill be retained. For otherwiſe the Miniſters, either durst not taxe the vices of their peculiar Benefactors, or, if they did, it would turne to their owne hurt.</hi> 3. <hi>That ſuſpicion of flattery might be eſchewed. For either the Miniſters would frame themſelues to pleaſe the weal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thier ſort, or, in caſe they did not, wicked and enuious people would iudge it ſo.</hi> 4. <hi>That the honour, ſhame faſtneſſe and honeſty of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters might be preſerued. For what ingenuous man would not be aſhamed, either to lay open his eſtate and pouerty to euery baſe fellow,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:21468:42"/>or to ſend forth his ſeruants to beg neceſſaries for him from dore to dore.</hi> 5. <hi>That all fraud and deceipt might be preuen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>on miniſters. who otherwiſe would neuer acknowledge themſelues wealthy, but would craftily diſſemble their eſtate.</hi> 6. <hi>That enuious worldlings might haue no cauſe to calumniate the Miniſters, to haue receiued more then indeed was giuen them.</hi> 7. <hi>That the poore people might not be preiudiced. For they must eyther contribute ſomething towards the Miniſters releefe, hauing more neede to be releeued themſelues, or they muſt endure ſhame for ſtaying their hands, when others ſhewed their liberality.</hi> 8. <hi>That men might not ſeeke occaſions to put away their Miniſters, vpon diſlike eyther of their continuall charge in maintay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning them, or of the liberty in reprehending their vices.</hi> 9.
<hi>That the miniſters might not ſeeme to be maintayned by wicked and vngodly perſons, Idolaters, Heretickes, Atheists, Swiggerers &amp;c. with whom good men ought to haue no communion.</hi> 10. <hi>That the Miniſters might not be burdenſome vnto the poore, to VVidowes, Pupils, Orphans, Sick, needy &amp;c. whom it were ſinne to rob.</hi> 11. <hi>That prodigall and arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant men might not, by their large contributions, take occaſion of boa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting, and extolling themſelues aboue others.</hi> 12. <hi>Becauſe there is no commaundement in holy ſcriptures, that Miniſters ſhould be ſo maintained in all places, and at all times.</hi> Let them be aſhamed, I ſay, of ſuch baſe popular exorbitant dependence, when they may be maintained with their Brethren at home, and feed of the fineſt of the wheate. Lo the malice, the enuy and ſpite, which we, whom they terme their
<hi>Accuſers,</hi> doe beare vnto them, God beeing wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe vnto our conſciences, that wee wiſh them all the good that may be.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Reuel. 7.12.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Amen. Praiſe, and Glory, and Wiſdome, and Thanks, and Honour, and Power, and Might, be vnto our God for euermore. Amen.</p>
            </q>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:21468:42"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
